<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.beehive.govt.nz/">
  <channel>
    <title>Beehive.govt.nz - The official website of the New Zealand Government</title>
    <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/</link>
    <description/>
    <language>en</language>
    
    <item>
  <title>Plain Language Act Repeal Bill passes first reading</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/plain-language-act-repeal-bill-passes-first-reading</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Legislation to repeal the Plain Language Act, which is a waste of time and money, has passed its first reading in Parliament today, Public Service Minister Judith Collins says.
“The Act, implemented by the previous government, compelled public service agencies to appoint designated 'plain language officers' and implement specific activities,” Ms Collins says.
“Rather than fix a problem, it created a problem whereby plain language officers had to be appointed, the Public Service Commission had to produce guidance documents and then agencies had to report to someone on something no one was quite clear on.
“That takes time, and time is money. It’s this sort of wasteful spending on bureaucracy that the Government is calling time on.
Repealing the Act means agencies will no longer be required to have a designated plain language officer.&nbsp;
“We need to trust the judgment and expertise of our public servants to communicate in language every taxpayer can grasp – without the need for designated officers or legal compulsion,” Ms Collins says.
“Repealing this Act cuts red tape and will allow the public service to get on with what really matters, which is delivering services for New Zealanders.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:42:54 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124732</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Government seeks to simplify Fringe Benefit Tax rules</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/government-seeks-simplify-fringe-benefit-tax-rules</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Inland Revenue is launching public consultation on proposals to make the Fringe Benefit Tax (FBT) rules easier&nbsp;and to reduce compliance costs for taxpayers, Revenue Minister Simon Watts says.
FBT is a tax payable when the following benefits are supplied to employees or shareholder-employees:

low interest/interest-free loans
free, subsidised, or discounted goods and services
employer contributions to sick, accident or death funds, superannuation schemes and specified insurance policies
motor vehicles available for private use
unclassified fringe benefits.

“Public feedback will help shape final proposals which Government will consider this year. The proposals have also been designed to be broadly fiscally neutral as the changes will focus on enhancing the integrity of the tax system,” Mr Watts says.
“Inland Revenue has been working with private sector experts to develop practical options for modernising the rules and to reduce compliance costs. We have already heard a lot of feedback from small businesses, and therefore, Inland Revenue has incorporated a proposal to move away from a focus on absolute accuracy of usage and instead adopting a ‘close enough is good enough’ approach which could take a lot of the compliance cost sting out of FBT.
“The focus of the proposals in the consultation document relates to motor vehicles and other small benefits and aims to simplify requirements and ease the compliance cost burden.
“The&nbsp;Fringe Benefit Tax was launched 40 years ago and, in that time, only a limited number of minor adjustments have been made to the rules.
“It is a quite fitting coincidence that consultation is being launched on the 40th anniversary of fringe benefit tax coming into effect.”
The consultation document is available at https://www.taxpolicy.ird.govt.nz/consultation/2025/fbt-options-for-change with consultation closing on 5 May.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:00:39 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124731</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Supporting better rehabilitation rates for injured Kiwis</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/supporting-better-rehabilitation-rates-injured-kiwis</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Updates to ACC’s Accredited Employers Programme taking effect today are designed to improve workplace injury rehabilitation for around one-fifth of New Zealand’s workforce and support our economic growth, says ACC Minister Scott Simpson.
“ACC’s fundamental purpose is to prevent injuries and get injured Kiwis back to independence as soon as possible. But rehabilitation rates have been slipping over the past decade, which is why they’re a crucial focus for me as I look to significantly improve ACC’s performance and long-term financial sustainability,” says Mr Simpson.
“The Accredited Employers Programme plays a big role in that – more than one in five full-time equivalent employees in New Zealand work for an accredited employer. I welcome the improvements ACC has made to enhance health and recovery outcomes for this substantial part of our workforce.”
The Programme allows sufficiently large employers to manage their employees’ claims for work injuries and occupational diseases in-house. In return for taking on the financial liability and claim management of work injuries, accredited employers receive a reduction in their work account levy.
The changes taking effect today include updates to improve performance monitoring and the way employers handle claims. These are the first substantive updates to the programme since its inception in 2000.
“The Accredited Employers Programme provides employers with a financial incentive to reduce workplace injuries and support staff to return to independence quickly,” says Mr Simpson.
“Ensuring employers help their employees get back to health and return to work makes absolute sense, as rehabilitation rates need serious improvement. These changes will ensure employers are meeting their obligations and providing the right support to their employees.”
Notes to editors
About the Accredited Employers Programme:

The Accredited Employers Programme includes some of New Zealand’s largest employers. There are around 130 employers in the programme, encompassing approximately 435,000 full time equivalent (FTE) employees, around 23 per cent of New Zealand’s total FTEs.
To remain in the Programme, Accredited Employers undertake an annual accreditation process, including an assessment, to ensure they are meeting all the requirements for the programme.&nbsp;

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:57:51 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124729</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Northland water security receives $41m boost </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/northland-water-security-receives-41m-boost</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Water projects in Northland will receive up to $41.5 million from the Regional Infrastructure Fund to significantly increase the region’s water security and unlock economic growth, Regional Development Minister Shane Jones says.
“These water projects together will significantly improve water storage and security in the Mid Far North and enable economic growth through consistent access to water and irrigation infrastructure for horticulture and land development,” Mr Jones says.
The funded projects are:&nbsp;

Otawere Pipeline&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; $24m loan
Kaipara Pipeline&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; $17.5m loan

The Otawere Pipeline project will see Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust consolidate the Otawere Reservoir on Waitangi River and expand its distribution network by 15km.
“This will&nbsp;provide water to a larger area of the community, and link to other key Mid Far North water storage projects to increase land-change opportunities in Kaikohe and surrounding areas,” Mr Jones says.&nbsp;
When it is completed, the infrastructure will enable 1600ha of productive land for Matawii, Waimate North and Mid North. The project will also employ 52 full-time staff during construction.
Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust will also receive up to $17.5m in the form of a loan to construct a 22km pipeline connecting the trust’s recently completed reservoir near Te Kopuru, to Dargaville.
“The Kaipara pipeline will extend to around 3000ha of prospective horticulture land between Te Kopuru and Dargaville and to Silver Fern Farm’s processing plant, the largest employer in the area.
“The plant faces challenges maintaining the continuous water supply it needs to keep operating throughout summer. Extending the pipeline to the processing plant will ensure a reliable water supply and continuous peak season operation,” Mr Jones says.
As part of this project, Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust and Kaipara District Council will combine the delivery of the Kaipara pipeline with an existing $7.8m Regional Infrastructure Fund flood resilience project, the Dargaville to Te Kōpuru stopbank upgrade.
The combined approach will lead to potential savings of $3m and a shorter delivery time through efficiencies across both projects.
“The Government’s investment in water is addressing barriers to development in regions like Northland, where a consistent water source is needed to unlock&nbsp;economic, environmental, and recreational resources for its communities,” Mr Jones says.
Editor’s note

The&nbsp;Regional Infrastructure Fund is a capital fund with the primary purpose of accelerating infrastructure projects, particularly with a focus on water storage, energy, and resilience, that will make a difference in the regions. 
Funding is approved in principle and announced, after which contracts are negotiated. Some funding may depend on updated information as agreed in contract negotiation. Payments are made once agreed milestones are met. These are set as part of contract negotiations and differ from project to project.
The Dargaville to Te Kōpuru Stopbank Upgrades project funding was approved by the Regional Development Ministers Group in July 2024.&nbsp;

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:52:53 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124728</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Elective boost delivers more than 2,000 procedures</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/elective-boost-delivers-more-2000-procedures</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Partnering with the private health sector is delivering better access and shorter wait times for elective treatment, Health Minister Simeon Brown.&nbsp;“Ensuring Kiwis have access to timely, quality healthcare is a priority for the Government.“Last month, I announced that Health New Zealand will be delivering an increase in elective procedures by partnering with private hospitals to make use of all available operating theatre capacity.&nbsp;“This work will see more than 10,579 additional procedures carried out between now and the middle of the year – and good progress is being made.“Delivery is ramping up, with more than 2,000 procedures completed so far. Priority is being given to patients waiting more than four months.&nbsp;“The most frequent procedures completed so far are cataracts, hip replacements, ear procedures, tonsillectomies, knee replacements, and hernia repairs.“We want to maximise capacity in the system so patients can get their surgery as quicky as possible.&nbsp;“Partnering closely with the private sector will enable Health New Zealand to get on top of waitlists, ensuring Kiwis get the surgeries they need when they need them.“This is key to achieving the Government’s health target of 95 per cent of patients to wait less than four months for elective treatment.“We are investing more in health than ever before – a record $30 billion each year. Our focus is on putting patients first, ensuring New Zealanders can get the surgeries they need as quickly as possible,” Mr Brown says.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:44:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124727</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Back to basics for public service</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/back-basics-public-service</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is overhauling the Public Service Act 2020 as part of its ongoing push to get back to basics and deliver value for money to taxpayers, Public Service Minister Judith Collins announced today.
The New Zealand National Party-ACT New Zealand Coalition Agreement requires the Act be amended to “clarify the role of the public service, drive performance and ensure accountability to deliver on the agenda of the government of the day”.
“The Public Service Act 2020, implemented by the previous government, added new responsibilities to the core role of chief executives which diminished their responsibility for implementing government policies and making efficient use of taxpayer money,” Ms Collins says.
“We don’t need to tell the chief executives of the public service which laws to follow. They just need to follow the law – like all other employers.
“The Act as it stands is impeding the public service from doing its best work, which in is in turn holding back the country from making progress on economic growth and other government priorities.”
The Public Service Amendment Bill will:

Clarify the role of the public service;
streamline chief executive responsibilities;
reinforce the principle of merit-based appointments;
improve chief executive and agency performance management;
utilise and improve tools to reduce silos; and
better manage risk.

“In the six years from 2017 to 2023, the number of people employed in the core Public Service grew 34% to 63,117 full-time equivalent employees,” Ms Collins says.
“Despite this whopping increase, the actual outcomes for New Zealanders went backwards across key areas such as health, education and crime. This is unacceptable.
“The efficiency, professionalism, and performance of the public service is a key resource for the Government and for New Zealanders, whose taxes pay for it.
“The changes we are making will bring more discipline to government spending and enable New Zealand’s economy to grow, creating more jobs, higher incomes and money to invest in core services such as schools, hospitals and roads.”
The Public Service Amendment Bill is expected to be introduced in July.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 13:09:16 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124726</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Public Works Act overhaul complete to drive infrastructure growth</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/public-works-act-overhaul-complete-drive-infrastructure-growth</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The final stage of reforms to the Public Works Act will introduce bigger and broader land payments, improved landowner engagement and new measures to support disaster recovery, Land Information Minister Chris Penk has announced.
“The Government has been working through an overhaul of the Public Works Act (PWA) to bring it into the 21st century after an independent review found it lacked clarity and commonsense. Today, I am proud to confirm that review is complete” Mr Penk says.
“If we want to grow the economy, boost productivity and make New Zealand a better place to live we must fix our pipes, increase the capacity of our schools and hospitals, and build more homes, roads and renewable energy sources.
“I want to thank the panel members for their expert advice in making the Act more efficient, effective, and transparent. This will help end decades of difficulties which have seen central and local governments struggle to secure land for development.
“Already announced changes include a dedicated carve-out in the law to provide incentive payments and a streamlined objections process for critical infrastructure. Now, this final set of reforms will modernise the wider system – protecting landowners’ rights while ensuring the Crown and local authorities can deliver for New Zealanders.”
The final tranche will:
Introduce incentive payments: To encourage early agreements on land acquisition, landowners who voluntarily sell their property before a Notice of Intention is issued will now be eligible for an incentive payment of 10 percent of the land value, up to a maximum of $100,000.
Update home-loss and land-loss payments: To recognise the disruption caused by acquisition, additional payments will be made alongside the land value and any incentive payments:

The home-loss base payment will increase from $35,000 to $50,000.
The land-loss payment amount will increase from $250-$25,000 to $350-$35,000.
Home-loss payments will now extend to multiple homes on a property, such as farms held in trust with multiple owners residing on the land.

Land Acquisition Process Reforms: The process for acquiring land will be streamlined by replacing the initial statutory notice with a more structured engagement process. Before issuing a Notice of Intention for compulsory acquisition:

Landowners must receive comprehensive information on the acquisition, their rights, entitlements, and an invitation to sell.
The Minister or local authority must negotiate with landowners in good faith for at least three months (or six months for Māori freehold land).

Emergency Provisions: New measures will allow land acquisition following a declared state of emergency to support infrastructure restoration and community recovery, when activated by Order in Council.
“Cyclone Gabrielle showed in the starkest light the immense challenges communities face after a natural disaster. When roads, railway lines, water and power stations are wiped out and homes left uninhabitable, we must act swiftly and decisively. This new emergency provision empowers us to reconnect those in need,” Mr Penk says.
The Public Works Act Amendment Bill will be introduced to Parliament in mid-2025, with the public invited to provide feedback through the select committee process.
Note to editors:
Information on previously announced Public Works Act changes can be found on the Beehive website:

Fairer compensation and safeguards for Māori landowners | Beehive.govt.nz
Going for Growth: Public Works Act overhaul | Beehive.govt.nz
Faster, fairer land acquisition to speed up infrastructure delivery | Beehive.govt.nz

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 12:30:27 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124725</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Freeing the great outdoors from health and safety scope creep</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/freeing-great-outdoors-health-and-safety-scope-creep</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Workplace Relations and Safety Minister Brooke van Velden is announcing further changes to health and safety, as part of the ACT-National Coalition commitment to reform health and safety law and regulations.
“This reform refocuses the work health and safety system by getting rid of over compliance, making sure there’s less paperwork and giving businesses, employers and workers clarity on their health and safety responsibilities. We want all New Zealanders to return home safely after every working day,” says Ms van Velden.
“For many Kiwis, outdoor recreational activities are a way of life that has been enjoyed for generations. Unfortunately, New Zealand’s work health and safety settings have reduced the appetite to allow these activities, inadvertently creating a culture of fear amongst landowners who are now worried about their legal liability if someone gets hurt,” says Ms van Velden.
“Many landowners, managers, councils, farmers and iwi allow access to their land for recreational use out of sheer goodwill. I do not think it is reasonable or proportionate for landowners, managers and iwi to be prosecuted by WorkSafe if someone was to be hurt or injured during the course of a recreational activity just because they are responsible for the land.
“Today I am announcing a change to the Health and Safety at Work Act that clarifies the law for landowners and will free up private and public land for recreational use.
“Landowners will not be responsible if someone is injured on their land while doing recreational activities. Health and safety responsibilities will lie squarely on the organisation running the activities,” says Ms van Velden.
“For example, a farmer might worry they are responsible for the risks of a horse trekking business on their land. I am making it clear in the law that in this case the health and safety duties sit with the horse trekking business. The farmer would only need to consider the risks from their work where that work is happening in the immediate vicinity of the horse trekking. They are not responsible for risks of the recreational activity itself.
“We all know that recreational activities aren’t without some risk, and sometimes it’s the risk that makes it fun. I want Kiwis to be able to hunt, fish, hike, climb, mountain bike, kayak and so much more without being caught up in health and safety red tape,” says Ms van Velden.
The change will apply to both public and private land, from farms and forestry to school grounds, local council land and regional and national parks.
This change will not impact private property rights, and it will still be up to the landowner to grant access to their land if they wish.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 11:10:09 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124723</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Māori economic growth plan aimed at boosting jobs and incomes</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/m%C4%81ori-economic-growth-plan-aimed-boosting-jobs-and-incomes</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Tōia mai te waka, ki te urunga te waka, ki te moenga te waka, ki te takotoranga i takoto ai te waka!
Creating jobs and boosting incomes is at the heart of a renewed Government Māori economic growth plan, Māori Development Minister Tama Potaka says.
“Today, the Government is releasing the ambitious Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori framework to boost Māori economic development.
"The framework has three main prongs: increasing infrastructure investment, accelerating exports and unlocking the potential of whenua Māori. This may expand or change in the future.
“The Māori contribution to the overall economy is growing fast, from $17 billion GDP in 2018 to $32 billion in 2023, and almost doubling in valued asset base. However, it continues to suffer from infrastructure deficits, barriers to accessing finance, and unproductive land laws.
“To address this, we will work together across Government and connect to the Government’s broader Going for Growth agenda. That's why the Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori framework has an initial focus on three key areas:

Increasing targeted infrastructure investment to drive employment and sustainable growth.For example, investment in Parininihi ki Waitōtara incorporation to accelerate work exploring the potential of a large-scale solar farm, capable of supplying over 8,500 homes. And the recent mahi tahi between the Government and Māori leaders at the Investment Infrastructure Summit.
Accelerating Māori business exports.For example, establishing a means to recognise traditional knowledge in the IP system that protects Māori point of difference and property rights.
Unlocking the growth potential of whenua Māori.For example, making targeted improvements to Te Ture Whenua Māori Act 1993 to simplify planning and related processes, encourage greater development opportunities and reduce red tape.

“To progress this mahi, Te Puni Kōkiri has released a public discussion document to encourage ideas and feedback on improving Te Ture Whenua Māori Act 1993.
“Māori land is often under-utilised, so we intend to make the Act more efficient, streamlined, and easier to navigate, with the aim of removing legislative barriers to economic development.
"It’s important that we hear from Māori landowners, whānau, hapū and iwi about these changes and I really encourage people to provide their feedback.”
Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori has been released alongside a discussion document for public consultation on proposed changes to Te Ture Whenua Maori Act 1993.
The discussion document is available on the Te Puni Kōkiri website. Consultation closes on May 23 2025.
Ko te whāinga a te mahere whakatupu ōhanga Māori he whakarea i ngā tūranga mahi me ngā whiwhinga utu
Tōia mai te waka, ki te urunga te waka, ki te moenga te waka, ki te takotoranga i takoto ai te waka!
Kei te ngako o te mahere whakatupu ōhanga Māori a te Kāwanatanga hou ko te waihanga tūranga mahi hou me te whakapiki ake i ngā whiwhinga utu, te kī a te Minita Whanaketanga Māori Tama Potaka.
“Nō te rangi nei, e whakarewa ana te Kāwanatanga i te anga pae tawhiti Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori hei hiki ake i te whanaketanga ōhanga Māori.
“E toru ngā marau matua o te anga: ko te whakapiki i te whakapaunga ki te hanganga, ko te whakahohoro ake i ngā hokotai, me te huaki i te pitomata o te whenua Māori. Ka whānui ake, ka rerekē rānei tēnei ā ngā tau e tū ake nei.
“Kua tere te piki haere o te takoha a te iwi Māori ki te ōhanga katoa o te motu, mai i te $17 piriona GDP i te tau 2018 ki te $32 piriona i te tau 2023, ka mutu, i tata tonu te whakatōpūtanga o te uara o te puna rawa. Heoi anō, nā te korenga o ētahi o ngā āhuatanga hanganga e tika ana, mai i ngā tauārai aukati pūtea tatū atu ki ngā ture whenua hua kore, kei te raru tonu, kei te raru tonu.
“Hei whakatikatika i tēnei, ka mahi tahi mātou puta noa i te Kāwanatanga me te tūhonohono ki kaupapa whānui a te Kāwanatanga Going for Growth. Koia te take e aro tuatahitia ana te anga Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori ki ngā wāhi matua e toru:

Te whakapiki ake i te whakapaunga pūtea ki te hanganga hei kōkiri i te whakapikinga o ngā tūranga mahi me te whakapūmautanga o te whakatupuranga.Hei tauira, ko te whakapaunga pūtea ki te kaporeihana o Parininihi ki Waiotōtara ki te whakatere ake i ngā mahi tūhura i te pitomata o te pāmu kōmaru nui tonu, e āhei ana ki te whāngai hihiko ki ngā kāinga neke atu i te 8,500. Me te mahi tahi o nā noa nei i waenga i ngā manukura o te Kāwanatanga me te iwi Māori ki te Hui Taumata mō te Whakapaunga Pūtea Hanganga.
Te whakatere ake i ngā hokotai pakihi Māori.Hei tauira, ko te whakaritenga o te ara hei āhukahuka i te mātauranga o neherā ki te pūnaha IP hei whakamarumaru i ngā tūāhuatanga ahurei me ngā motika rawa o te Māori.
Te huaki i te pitomata tupuranga o te whenua Māori.Hei tauira, ko ngā whakatikatika i arotahitia ki Te Ture Whenua Māori 1993 ki te whakangāwari i ngā hātepe me ngā tukanga whai pānga, te whakatenatena i ngā arawātea whakawhanake, me te whakamarino i ngā wai karekare o te hunga kātipa.

“Hei kauneke haere i tēnei mahi, kua whakaputaina e Te Puni Kōkiri te tuhinga matapakinga mā te iwi whānui hei whakatenatena i ngā ariā me ngā urupare e pā ana ki te whakapaitanga ake i Te Ture Whenua Māori 1993.
“He nui ngā wā kāore i kaha te whakamahia o te whenua Māori, nō reira ko tō mātou koronga kia pai, kia kakama ake te whakahaere, kia ngāwari ake hoki te whakatere, me te whai kia whakakorea ngā tauārai ā-ture ki te whakawhanaketanga ā-ōhanga.
“He mea nui kia rongo mai mātou i ngā kaipupuri whenua Māori, ngā whānau, ngā hapū me ngā iwi i ngā kōrero mō ēnei huringa, ka mutu, kei te tino whakamanawa au i ngā tāngata ki te whakahoki mai i ā rātou kōrero urupare.
Kua whakaputaina ko te Going for Growth with Māori | Tōnui Māori ki te taha o te tuhinga matapakinga mō te rūnanga tūmatanui e pā ana ki ngā huringa ki Te Ture Whenua Māori 1993 kua whakatakotoria.
E wātea ana te tuhinga matapakinga ki te paetukutuku o Te Puni Kōkiri. Ka kati te matapakinga ā te 23 o Haratua, 2025.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 07:51:38 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124722</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Going for growth: cutting health &amp; safety red tape</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/going-growth-cutting-health-safety-red-tape</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government will boost economic growth by reforming health and safety laws to lessen the cost and burden of compliance on low-risk businesses, Workplace Relations and Safety Minister Brooke van Velden says.
“We’re delivering on the ACT-National coalition agreement to reform health and safety laws and regulations. We want all Kiwis to return home safe after every working day.&nbsp;
“I have travelled across the country meeting with businesses, employers, and workers about how the current system works for them and what they want to see in this reform that will make their work safer. What I have been hearing consistently is that small, low-risk businesses are not sure which risks to focus on and struggle to meet the costs of compliance.
“I’ve listened and I’m acting. Cabinet has today agreed to a suite of system-wide changes, including sharpening the Health and Safety at Work Act 2015, to cut through the unnecessary red tape holding these businesses back.
“The first change will be a carve-out for small, low-risk businesses from general Health and Safety at Work Act requirements. These businesses will only have to manage critical risks and provide basic facilities to ensure worker welfare.
“For example, a small clothing shop would still need to provide first aid, emergency plans, and basic facilities, such as suitable lighting, but wouldn’t need to have a psychosocial harm policy in place.
“This will improve outcomes for businesses and workers by focusing the system on critical risks and getting rid of unnecessary costs, making sure there is less paperwork and more clarity on what will make workplaces safe.”
Cabinet has also agreed to:

Reduce tick-box health and safety activities that do not protect workers from harm by sharpening the primary purpose of the Health and Safety at Work Act to focus on critical risk,
Address over-compliance due to overlapping health and safety duties by clarifying the boundaries between the Act and regulatory systems that already manage the same risk,
Cut compliance costs by reducing notification requirements to the regulator to only significant workplace events (deaths, serious injury, illness and incidents),
Help end the proliferation of road cones by providing a hotline for the public to report overzealous road cone use, and for WorkSafe to confirm and provide guidance on instances of over-compliance.

I’ve travelled across the country to hear health and safety concerns, and at nearly every meeting, someone raised the issue of sea of road-cones. I am directing WorkSafe to confirm and provide guidance on instances of road cones overcompliance. Having WorkSafe focus on this will be a culture shift for the agency, but it signifies the broader direction this Government is taking with the health and safety system.&nbsp;
“These changes are just the start of the Government’s reform programme. I will be seeking Cabinet decisions in the coming months that will further improve WorkSafe and address sector-specific pain points.
“Workers can be assured that their employers will prioritise the right actions to protect them from harm, and they know where their attention should be to keep themselves and their workmates safe.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:35:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124721</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Help shape the future of farm plastics recycling</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/help-shape-future-farm-plastics-recycling</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is encouraging New Zealanders, particularly in rural areas, to share their views on proposed regulations to improve the management of farm plastic waste, Environment Minister Penny Simmonds says.
"The proposal – an industry-led initiative – would bring the existing Agrecovery and Plasback programmes into a single national recycling system, making services simpler and more accessible for all users of regulated farm plastics," Ms Simmonds says.
The proposed regulations would support a nationally consistent product stewardship scheme for agrichemicals, their containers, and farm plastics, helping farmers and growers reduce their environmental impact while maintaining productivity.
“Plastic products are vital to New Zealand’s world-leading agri-economy, but rural communities know that waste like agrichemical containers and bale wrap can quickly pile up,” Ms Simmonds says.
“These regulations will provide a unified system where producers, sellers, and users take responsibility for the entire product lifecycle, from design to disposal.”
Public consultation, opening today, will focus on regulations supporting the new product stewardship scheme, provisionally named Green-farms. In addition to farmers and growers, industries such as forestry, manufacturing, hospitality, and tourism, as well as local authorities and households, would have access to national take-back services.
“The scheme offers a practical solution for a wide range of consumers, including households needing proper disposal options for pest and weed control product containers,” Ms Simmonds says.
The programme will ensure farmers have access to free-to-use drop-off sites and collection services while working alongside regulations for producers and importers.
“Key industry stakeholders back the scheme, which offers a better alternative to burning or burying plastic waste on farms. Rural communities want a simple, effective system, and we welcome feedback to refine the proposed regulations,” Ms Simmonds says.
Consultation on the new regulations will run until 1 June 2025.
Information and submission forms are now available: Proposed product stewardship regulations for agrichemicals, their containers, and farm plastics - Ministry for the Environment - Citizen Space
Further information:
Agrichemicals and their containers, and farm plastics are one of six priority products for which stewardship schemes must be implemented under the Waste Minimisation Act 2008: Priority product stewardship | Ministry for the Environment
Read more about the scheme: Agrecovery's Green-farms Product Stewardship Scheme accredited to create more recycling opportunities for farmers - Agrecovery
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 15:30:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124720</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Rail ferries and straightforward infrastructure </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/rail-ferries-and-straightforward-infrastructure</link>
  <description><![CDATA[[Speech delivered in the Legislative Council Chamber, Parliament, to media at the announcement of the decision on the future of the interisland ferries]
Welcome.
First, can we acknowledge Chris Mackenzie, the Chair of Ferry Holdings who is here today, and directors Heather Simpson, Greg Lowe, Katherine Rich and Captain Iain Macleod.
They have worked hard, but they have not worked alone. Sensible people from across Port Marlborough, CentrePort and KiwiRail have come to the fore and we thank them all.
On the 11th of December, we resumed responsibility for the Rail portfolio and with it the leadership of the Cook Strait ferry replacement programme.
We said then that we would outline the key ship and infrastructure decisions by the end of March.
Today is the 31st of March.
The programme we cancelled
The iReX programme, which our Government cancelled in December 2023, should be studied by members of the public who want to see their tax dollars respected.
It is a cautionary tale.
In 2020, when we were responsible for KiwiRail, we committed $400.1 million as a taxpayer contribution to buying two new ferries and readying the infrastructure for them.
Back then, the total cost of that programme was supposed to be $1.4 billion, with most costs financed by KiwiRail and the ports.
This arrangement placed the commercial incentive on the companies to keep the costs low.
What happened between 2021, when the ship contract was signed, and 2023 when the truth came out about this project is as follows:
The project leaders approached this task as though they were pricing the job, not delivering it.
They did so because the previous Government gave them every reason to believe they would get their way.
The only method to stop behaviour like that is to do exactly as the Minister of Finance did in December 2023.
Today, we have vindicated the decision of the Minister of Finance to stop the project.
Project iReX was said to cost $3.1 billion according to KiwiRail, while officials warned the previous Government it would approach $4 billion.
Taking a charitable view of the world by accepting KiwiRail’s estimate, that meant the infrastructure costs alone would be $2.6 billion.
The vast bulk of this cost was expected from you, the taxpayer.
We said no. We could do better. So here is what we will do.
What we will deliver on ferries
By Christmas 2029, two new Interislander ferries will enter service on the Strait. They will get you, your family, the caravan, the dog and all the rest across the Strait.
New ferries mean we are buying for a full-service life of 30 years. We are looking to the long term.
These ferries will be about 200 metres in length, and about 28 metres in width. That is longer and wider than the current Interislander fleet of three, meaning it has capacity to serve current and future demand.
Both ferries will have capacity for 1,500 passengers.
Crucially, these ferries will be smaller than what the previous Government contracted in 2021. That saves us materially on infrastructure.
The Cook Strait is also an essential connection for the movement of our goods and services. It has a freight task to serve, and these ferries will do exactly that.
Trucks will drive onto these ferries.
Rail will shunt onto these ferries.
Both ferries will have 2.4 kilometres of lanes for trucks and cars, with space for 40 rail wagons.
We serve both, because they serve every business stretching across our provinces and our cities in New Zealand.
The reason for this is just plain common sense. Road-only ferries would require us to reconfigure the whole operation, at considerable costs.
Road and rail ferries mean we shunt large freight volumes in single movements. That saves time, and time is money.
This is not the Ministerial Advisory Group’s plan
The Ministerial Advisory Group proposed the Government buy two road-only ferries, said it would be cheaper overall, and that we should approach just one shipyard to do a deal.
We did not accept that advice. We believe in competitive tenders, and a full appreciation of what best serves our country.
And road-only ferries came out as more expensive than buying road and rail ferries.
What we will deliver on infrastructure
The surest way to keep infrastructure costs low is to use what you’ve already got.
The marine infrastructure in Picton requires replacement, so it will be replaced. The marine infrastructure in Wellington has life left in it, so we will modify and keep using it.
This level of pragmatism was completely absent under iReX.
The road and rail marshalling yards will be modestly modified, but not completely renewed like under iReX. These yards were built by our forebears. They knew what they were doing. We know it because these yards have served us well for decades.
The road connections in Wellington and Picton will also be improved, in discussion with those councils.
The terminal buildings in Wellington and Picton will remain as they are today. While some may regret the absence of a Taj Mahal in Picton and the Sydney Opera House in Wellington, the people paying their taxes will not.
And need we remind you that the main experience people have when they wait to board the ship is not the terminal building, it’s their own vehicle. For those walking on, it’s the ship that gives the experience, not the walkway.
The time will come when new terminal buildings will be needed, and space is allocated for when the ports are ready. But they are not needed now, and not at your expense.
Our new wharf in Picton is looking to the future. It will have a dual-level linkspan and double lanes. That means unloading and offloading will be faster in Picton than it is today.
While Wellington remains single lane, as this saves the taxpayer considerable money, the time will come when the port companies invest in double-lane infrastructure.
The door to the port’s long-term aspirations remains open, but we are focused on what’s needed right here, right now.
The next steps
So, today our Government has agreed to buy two new ferries to serve our people, cars, trucks and rail.
Our Government has agreed to a pragmatic infrastructure solution that focused on minimum viable, maximum reuse.
We have said yes to affordability, and no to extravagance.
This gives the small Ferry Holdings team the mandate they need to negotiate a good ship contract with commercial shipyards.
Ferry Holdings now has key ship decisions, which enables them to finalise the ship specifications and invite a shortlist of shipyards into a closed tender process.
These shipyards won’t know who each other are, and they will compete on price and quality.
Ferry Holdings also has key infrastructure decisions, and a firm budget to live within. This enables them to progress the engineering and construction programme with both ports and KiwiRail.
They will keep a firm hand on the tiller to keep scope and costs under control. And the ports will share this view, as their dollars are on the line too.
We have decided in the national interest to directly purchase ships and proceed with an infrastructure plan that meets our needs.
We’re buying ships and sorting infrastructure, and what must follow is a commercially disciplined business to safely, reliably and affordably serve our people and their goods.
Programme cost
And for those in the media who want to know, ‘how much will this cost,’ let us say this: we will not approach this like Wellington Water, by which we mean revealing our budget while negotiating the price. That turns a buyers’ market into a sellers’ market.
When the ship and port agreements are signed later this year, you will know the total cost and the shares between the Government and the ports.
In the meantime, it should be patently obvious to even the most casual observer that an infrastructure programme that makes use of what is already there will be markedly cheaper than the iReX programme which sought to knock everything down and build utopia in its place.
Port Marlborough, CentrePort and KiwiRail have approached this with a focus on pragmatism, cost-effectiveness, and a heavy dose of reality. Together with Ferry Holdings, they have a single plan to concentrate on now, and to deliver on.
And we will back them all the way.
Thank you very much.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:01:32 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124719</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Rail ferries and straightforward infrastructure </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/rail-ferries-and-straightforward-infrastructure</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Rail Minister Winston Peters has announced the plan for two new rail ferries to enter service in 2029, continuing the 60-year legacy of the Interislander connecting New Zealanders and their goods.
Cabinet today agreed the package which Mr Peters says will deliver the appropriate ships and infrastructure for the job at a significant saving for the taxpayer.
“Our solution will be markedly cheaper than the cancelled $3.1 billion programme and the $4 billion warning the previous Government received. That’s because of a minimum viable and maximum reuse approach for the port infrastructure,” Mr Peters says.
“The future Interislander ferries will have road and rail decks, given the efficiency of single shunt movements for multiple rail wagons for loading and unloading.
“The design specifications chosen include vessel lengths of approximately 200 metres – longer and wider than the current fleet and capable of serving our people and goods into the future, but shorter than the large ferries ordered in 2021 which created significant infrastructure issues.”
Mr Peters says in addition to selecting the appropriate rail ferry specifications, getting the infrastructure right is essential for a cost-effective solution.
“The marine infrastructure in Picton requires replacement, so it will be replaced. The marine infrastructure in Wellington has life left in it, so it will be modified and re-used.
“Our analysis showed this to be the most cost-effective option, and contrasts sharply with the wanton demolition and extravagant specification under the cancelled project, where they assumed almost all costs would be at the taxpayers’ expense.
“We are extraordinarily grateful to our small Ferry Holdings team and the hard work put in across the three companies,” Mr Peters says.
Now the mode and specifications have been selected, the Ferry Holdings Board will shortlist shipyards to compete on price and quality, with a ferry contract awarded later this year. Ferry Holdings will also work with Port Marlborough, CentrePort and KiwiRail to finalise the scope, progress engineering, strengthen the delivery programme and agree co-funding terms.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:00:03 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124718</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Patterson leads the running of the sheep at the Great NZ Muster</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/patterson-leads-running-sheep-great-nz-muster</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Te Kūiti’s Great New Zealand Muster is a fantastic opportunity to celebrate the sheep and the farmers, and the invaluable role they play in our communities and regional economies, says Associate Minister of Agriculture Mark Patterson.
Mr Patterson, known as the ‘Minister for Wool’, joined the front of the Great NZ Muster running of the Sheep down the main street of Te Kūiti today.&nbsp;
“It’s a great honour to be part of this iconic event, which demonstrates the vibrant spirit of our rural communities.”
The event is combined with NZ Shears, one of New Zealand’s premiere shearing events, where you can see world class shearers in action – and big contributors to the rural community.
“For me, it’s also a chance to reflect on the state of the wool sector and the positive steps the government and industry are taking to turn it around – supporting the NZ wool industry is a key part in doubling the value of NZ exports.”
“The recent bar that we have crossed is that&nbsp;wool prices now cover the shearing costs, which is something that we have been working hard at to change, but we know there is much more to be done. I am more confident than ever that we can turn around the fortunes of wool.”
“There is a swing back to natural fibres – we’re seeing good gains, with strong wool price steadily increasing over the last 18 months to be now sitting around $4 per kg (clean), which is an eight-year high.”
“Wool exports were worth NZD $549 million in the year to 30 June 2024, up from NZD $513 million in the previous year.”
“New Zealand is the largest exporter of strong wool, accounting for 20 percent of the 500 million kilograms of strong wool produced globally – and we want to remain on top and&nbsp;deliver higher and more sustainable pricing for our farmers.”
“Together with key players in the sector, we’re investing time, energy, and money into innovation and new uses to lift the demand for strong wool.”
“To date, 20&nbsp;strong wool projects from across the value-chain have been approved for funding, with $17.8 million of government investment via the Ministry for Primary Industries and co-funding of $22.9 million from industry partners, for a total of $40.7 million.”
“These projects are focused on finding&nbsp;high-value opportunities for our strong wool, facilitating collaboration, and improving sector and supply chain capability.”
“Projects that have received funding include&nbsp;Bremworth’s 100 percent, fully compostable wool carpets and rugs, and T&amp;R Interior Systems’ Floc wool acoustic panel – both with huge potential to boost returns for our wool farmers significantly.”&nbsp;

Mr Patterson says he hopes that the&nbsp;Great New Zealand Muster will act as a springboard for thinking about the benefits of strong wool.&nbsp;
“New Zealand wool was once the backbone of New Zealand’s economy and I remain excited about the future of the wool industry as we tap into new high value opportunities.”

“I will&nbsp;continue to work with farmers to rebuild the industry into a strong sector that recognises its exporting and sustainability potential” says Mr Patterson.


  

  
              



      



]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 14:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124717</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Reserve Bank capital review welcomed </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/reserve-bank-capital-review-welcomed</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Reserve Bank’s decision to review its capital requirements has been welcomed by Finance Minister Nicola Willis.
“Submissions made to the finance and expenditure committee’s banking inquiry have raised concerns that New Zealand’s bank capital regime is too conservative, and that this is undermining banking competition, driving up the cost of lending and reducing growth in the New Zealand economy.
“I share these concerns and welcome the Reserve Bank Board’s decision to conduct an evidence-based review of its capital regime, using international experts, and comparing New Zealand’s requirements with those in comparable countries.&nbsp;
“It’s important that the Reserve Bank’s prudential regime preserves the stability of our financial system, while taking care not to not impose excessive costs in the process.&nbsp;
“Higher capital requirements increase the cost of borrowing. This can reduce economic activity and drive up the cost of living. I want to see settings that preserve financial stability while encouraging investment, job creation and income growth.&nbsp;
“Submitters have argued that other countries have less onerous bank capital requirements and that New Zealand is becoming an outlier internationally.&nbsp;
“The Reserve Bank’s decision to conduct a prompt review is a good opportunity to objectively assess New Zealand’s settings and consider whether the Bank’s intention to keep increasing capital requirements still makes sense.”&nbsp;
The Reserve Bank increase in minimum capital requirements followed a review in 2017-2019 and is being implemented over seven years with annual increases on 1 July each year.&nbsp;
The big banks are currently required to maintain minimum capital of 13.5 per cent and the smaller banks minimum capital of 11.5 per cent. The Reserve Bank has been planning to, by 2028, lift those requirements to 18 and 16 per cent respectively.
“I welcome the Reserve Bank’s willingness to step back and consider whether decisions it made several years ago are still in step with domestic and international developments.”
Decisions about bank capital requirements are taken independently by the RBNZ Board in accordance with the Bank's financial stability objective.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 10:19:39 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124715</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Delivering better grocery prices    </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/delivering-better-grocery-prices</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Today I am announcing next steps in the Government’s mission to deliver better grocery prices for Kiwis.
Our Government knows that the cost of living is a major concern for New Zealanders. We are focused on delivering changes that will bring down the cost of living, now and in the years ahead.
One major driver of the cost of living is the high prices many Kiwis pay for their basic groceries. After housing, food is the second-most expensive item in Kiwis’ household budgets.
The current situation
New Zealand grocery prices are high by international standards. Kiwi shoppers are being poorly served by extremely low levels of competition in our grocery sector.&nbsp;
This lack of competition is the result of a series of mergers that have occurred over the past 30 or 40 years, reducing a sector once characterised by a number of grocery chains to a market now dominated by just two major players per island:&nbsp; Foodstuffs North Island, Foodstuffs South Island&nbsp; (with the New World, Pak ‘n Save and Four Square brands) and Woolworths (with the Countdown and Fresh Choice / Super Value brands).
These incumbents exhibit significant market power and act as an effective island duopoly, with many communities experiencing what could be characterised as a localised grocery monopoly, as they have no other store to choose from near their homes.
It's noteworthy that Foodstuffs argued in the courts that the merger of Progressive Enterprises and Woolworths NZ was not in consumers’ interests.&nbsp;
This dynamic was acknowledged by a 2022 market study and led to a series of reforms.&nbsp; &nbsp;
In September last year the Commerce Commission published its first annual report into the grocery sector, which provided an update on the impact of reforms so far.&nbsp;
It concluded that competition in the grocery sector had not materially improved.
The Commerce Commission did note pockets of improved competition due, for example, to Costco entering the Auckland market, and the Warehouse expanding its range of grocery offerings. But these incursions have not fundamentally changed the competitive dynamics in the market.
There has been no reduction in market concentration, with evidence of increasing margins for major supermarkets, and ongoing levels of profitability much higher than would be expected in a workably competitive market.
There have also been recent examples of firms struggling to compete in the market. Organic grocer Huckleberry, which owned three stores in Auckland, went into liquidation in 2024. Online grocer Supie was put into voluntary administration in October 2023.&nbsp; &nbsp;
The Grocery Commissioner has noted the disappointing impact of new wholesale regulations, and ongoing problems with the Grocery Supply Code.
The simple reality is this: Despite good intentions, the last Government’s reforms have not improved grocery competition or delivered better prices for Kiwi supermarket shoppers.&nbsp;
I am advised that without further action, meaningful changes to competition will be some time away.&nbsp;
Progress Update
Last month I announced my desire to see another competitor enter the supermarket scene to deliver more effective competition in the grocery sector, disrupt the major players, drive down prices and increase options for Kiwi shoppers.
I made clear then that the Government wants to help remove barriers that could get in the way of a new entrant, including potentially removing a range of regulatory hurdles.&nbsp;
Since February, I and my officials have engaged with a range of interested parties who’ve shared their views of what might be needed to help their entry or expansion into the New Zealand grocery market.
These engagements have been instructive.&nbsp; My key findings have been:

To achieve the best outcomes for consumers we need at least one competitor entering or expanding to operate at a national scale. The Commerce Commission’s first grocery report supports this view, stating that success in the grocery industry “requires a third major network of supermarkets, offering a full range of groceries nationwide”.
That the Government’s work to replace the Resource Management Act, and changes to the Overseas Investment Act can help to ease the path for new grocery stores.
That the Commerce Commission’s work to target multiple other issues – including on wholesale supply of groceries, monitoring of anti-competitive behaviour and strengthening information and protections for consumers and suppliers - must continue at pace.
That further bespoke regulatory intervention could help some potential entrants – including by addressing potential barriers in food labelling and import standards that could prevent the importation of competitor products.
That even with all these changes, major commercial and regulatory barriers could still prevent a third player from being able to enter or compete at a national scale.

A competitor at scale
This final point is very important.
I want to see a new grocery competitor that can introduce competitive pressure not just in one niche or region but across the country, so that it improves shopping choices and prices for as many Kiwi shoppers as possible.&nbsp;
International experience suggests that for this to occur, a new player would probably need to reach a scale of at least 10% of the existing market and do so relatively quickly.
There are a range of views about what additional interventions could be needed to make that possible. Some suggest that progressing the current Commerce Commission work programme, in conjunction with consenting and investment reform may be sufficient.&nbsp;
Others advocate more significant changes to the structure of the New Zealand grocery market.&nbsp;
These include splitting existing brands currently housed under one umbrella back into separate businesses (horizontal separation or demerger); splitting wholesale and retail provision of groceries (vertical separation); divestment approaches explored but ultimately put on hold by the previous Government, or a combination of these approaches.
In light of this work, and the advice and views I have considered to date, I have now made recommendations to Cabinet about the next steps needed to improve competition in the New Zealand grocery sector.
Issuing a formal “Request for Information” to support a supermarket competitor
Today I am announcing that Cabinet has agreed to commence a formal Request For Information (RFI) process to accelerate improved competition in the New Zealand retail grocery market.
The RFI I am releasing will help the Government identify the next regulatory and legislative steps needed to support a significant national-scale competitive challenge to the New Zealand supermarket duopoly.
We want to know what it would take for one or more new grocery retailers to enter the grocery market on a national scale, or existing competitors to grow to sufficient size to generate a material increase in the level of competition in the New Zealand grocery sector.&nbsp;
We want to hear from firms or groups who have the capability and capacity to provide New Zealand consumers with a full range of grocery products, at scale, nationwide.&nbsp;
This is about obtaining detailed information about how the Government can support a new supermarket competitor, using the full range of legislative and regulatory tools available to us.
We are asking respondents to set out the ideal conditions that would need to exist for them to enter and grow in the New Zealand retail grocery market.&nbsp;I also want to hear about barriers, both commercial and regulatory, and what the Government can do to improve conditions to allow them to set up and better compete with the incumbents.&nbsp;
For example, they may face barriers securing appropriate sites to build on, or they may have issues accessing supply, or there may be fundamental issues with the structure of the market.
I expect that a new competitor would need to have, buy or build a substantial physical store network. That is a big ask. We can’t just cross our fingers and wait for that to happen. Nor am I satisfied that we’ve yet flushed out everyone who might be up for the task – if we get the conditions right.
As such, I have asked officials to seek responses from firms which already have a presence in the New Zealand market, such as Costco and the Warehouse as well as established overseas grocery firms, such as Coles, Aldi and Lidi. Investors for targeting will include general investment funds, specialist infrastructure investors and iwi groups.&nbsp;
I have also asked officials to seek views from the existing major players, alongside the smaller store owners who work under their brands, to ensure their perspectives are heard.
The scale of the challenge
The challenges facing a major new competitor should not be underestimated.
My engagements to date have suggested that for so long as the current duopoly structure continues, and even with targeted regulatory action, potential investors may perceive that the commercial barriers to success in the NZ grocery market are just too high.&nbsp;
Initial research suggests a new or expanding national-scale grocery competitor would require significant upfront capital.&nbsp; It’s expected that the RFI will expose the “J Curve“” for investment, that is the potential for upfront losses that would be incurred during set-up followed by larger returns down the line.&nbsp;
Any large new supermarket business would need to compete with what are large, well-established retailers, with strong brand recognition, substantial market power and significant efficiencies of scale.&nbsp;
Concerns include the difficulty in obtaining suitable store sites at scale and pace, the potential for existing players to use their market power to block or squeeze out new entrants and the potential for existing players to place pressure on suppliers to offer less advantageous terms to new entrants.&nbsp;
I want potential participants in the Government’s RFI to know I understand the mountain we are asking them to climb.&nbsp;
It’s important they take this opportunity to articulate potential challenges as plainly as possible.&nbsp;
Further options for Government Intervention
I acknowledge that we can’t just wait for another competitor to arrive.
In order to make the New Zealand grocery sector more competitive sooner it’s possible more significant reform of the underlying grocery market structure may be required.&nbsp;
I have therefore advised Cabinet that when I report back to them later this year I will potentially recommend progressing additional intervention options for the New Zealand grocery market, including new legislation, should I view this as necessary to achieve the increased levels of grocery competition we are seeking for New Zealand shoppers.
I am actively anticipating what that may involve.
Accordingly, I am also announcing today that I am considering a possible structural separation of existing entities in the New Zealand grocery sector.
To support this, I have commissioned specialist external advice on ways in which the existing supermarket duopoly could be restructured to improve competition, including advice on options for ‘de-merger’ of existing brands, the potential impacts of structural separation of existing entities, and concepts for how this could be achieved.
It’s important this work, and any recommendations I make to Cabinet, are informed by the responses the Government receives to the Request for Information we are issuing today.&nbsp;
And that resulting recommendations properly consider the potential benefits – and costs – of intervention.&nbsp;
In considering potential design options I consider any newly created market structure would need to deliver net consumer benefits from greater competition, be enduring, ensure the market is dynamic and efficient and ensure that any transaction costs are kept to a minimum.
I do not take this step lightly.&nbsp;
In a global context, the New Zealand grocery market has experienced exceptional consolidation, a point that the OECD and other international experts agree is major cause for concern.
This is a $27 billion sector – roughly the size of New Zealand’s tourism and dairy sales combined – so it’s crucial that we get this market working effectively.&nbsp;
Doing so will deliver benefits into every shopping trolley and create new business opportunities up and down the supply chain.
I want to emphasise once again that this Government is not looking to run a supermarket chain: there will be no KiwiShop.&nbsp;
Next steps&nbsp;
I know that while this work progresses, Kiwi shoppers, feeling the pinch at the checkout, will remain impatient.&nbsp;
They have already waited too long for more competitive grocery offerings.
We need to move fast, and also with due care.&nbsp;
The RFI will proceed at pace, with information sought in the next six weeks. Work on market structure options will continue while this occurs, as will the Commerce Commission’s work to complete its wholesale inquiry, its analysis into land-banking issues and its second grocery report.
In mid 2025, once I have considered the evidence coming in from the RFI, and the Commission’s work, I will bring further recommendations to Cabinet. Depending on what I hear, I may seek Cabinet’s mandate to progress further design work on structural options to improve competition in the grocery sector.
If legislation is needed, I would want to introduce it before the end of the year and pass it during this parliamentary term, with rapid implementation shortly thereafter.&nbsp;
I am determined that this be a thorough and considered process. It’s vital we get this right.&nbsp;
As I said, I take seriously the need to weigh carefully not only the potential benefits of further intervention, but also its potential costs. And, it’s important to note, Cabinet has not yet formed a view on whether structural intervention will, in fact, be needed.&nbsp;
The RFI we are issuing today is a crucial step for informing our future deliberations. I can’t yet predict the detailed recommendations I will make as a result.&nbsp;
It could also be the case that the incumbent supermarkets propose actions that would prevent the need for any new legislation – for example through voluntary divestment undertakings under section 69A of the Commerce Act.
My key message is this: if further intervention is needed to drive competition in the grocery sector, then I’m up for it.&nbsp;
I’m putting all options on the table.&nbsp;
I’ll now take your questions.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 11:12:30 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124713</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Going for Growth: all supermarket options on table </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/going-growth-all-supermarket-options-table</link>
  <description><![CDATA[All options are on the table to deliver a better deal for supermarket shoppers, Economic Growth Minister Nicola Willis says.
“Today I am issuing a Request for Information (RFI) asking potential supermarket challengers – both in New Zealand and overseas –what regulatory changes are needed to help them compete at a national scale and drive grocery prices down.
“At the same time, I have asked officials for advice on ways in which the grocery sector could be restructured to increase competition.
“New Zealand grocery prices are high by international standards and Kiwi shoppers are being poorly served by a market effectively dominated by just two major players - Foodstuffs and Woolworths.
“This lack of competition is the result of a series of mergers that have occurred over the past 30 or 40 years.&nbsp;
“Despite well-intended reforms in recent years, competition in the grocery market has not improved. Kiwis are still missing out on competitive grocery offerings.
“The purpose of the RFI is to identify the regulatory and legislative steps necessary to facilitate increased competition at scale.
“I am seeking information from a range of potential investors, on what it would take for one or more new grocery retailers to enter the market on a national scale, or for existing competitors to grow to sufficient size to materially increase competition.
“I also want to know what regulatory and commercial barriers to competing potential new entrants see and what they would like the Government to do about those barriers.
“I am concerned that more significant action may be required to foster genuine competition. Therefore, I have commissioned specialist external advice on ways in which the existing supermarket duopoly could be restructured to improve competition.
“Officials are working with the appointed advisors to consider options including a possible demerger of existing entities.
“In mid 2025, once I have considered the evidence coming in from the RFI, and the Commission’s work, I will bring further recommendations to Cabinet.”
“No decisions have been made yet, but if Cabinet decides legislation is necessary, I expect to introduce it to Parliament by the end of the year.”&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2025 11:10:09 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124712</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Infrastructure Minister to visit Singapore </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/infrastructure-minister-visit-singapore</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Infrastructure and Transport Minister Chris Bishop will travel to Singapore this week to build on the momentum from the NZ Infrastructure Investment Summit and show New Zealand is ‘open for business’.
“The NZ Infrastructure Investment Summit was a real success, with huge interest from around the world in investing in New Zealand,” says Mr Bishop.&nbsp;
“In Singapore I will meet with a range of pension funds and investment companies, including Temasek and GIC, to talk about New Zealand’s infrastructure pipeline and government reforms to welcome international investment.
“New Zealand infrastructure company Morrison is expanding their office in Singapore and it will be a pleasure to formally launch their new office. As one of the world’s largest specialist infrastructure managers, Morrison is a real New Zealand success story.
“Singapore is one of our most important partners in Southeast Asia, and one of our largest sources of foreign investment. This year marks the 60th anniversary of diplomatic relations between New Zealand and Singapore, a significant milestone that underscores the depth and strength of our partnership.
“I will also meet with Minister Grace Fu, Singapore’s Minister for Sustainability and the Environment and Minister-in-charge of Trade Relations, to discuss renewable energy, resilient infrastructure, and infrastructure investment.
“We have a lot to learn from Singapore, particularly around transport and infrastructure and I am looking forward to meetings to discuss rapid transit, public housing, and port development.”
Mr Bishop leaves for Singapore on Sunday 30 March and is due to return on Thursday 3 April.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 15:00:27 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124711</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Entering final stages of Ngāti Hāua settlement </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/entering-final-stages-ng%C4%81ti-h%C4%81ua-settlement</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Crown and Ngāti Hāua are now entering the final stages of their settlement after agreeing on the terms at Ngāpuwaiwaha Marae in Taumarunui today, Treaty Negotiations Minister Paul Goldsmith says.
"It is an honour to be able to sign a Deed of Settlement and deliver a Crown apology after eight years of negotiations.
“This means we can now get legislation underway to put through the house at pace. Treaty Negotiations are a major priority for this Government.
"This settlement includes an agreed historical account and redress for historical breaches of Te Tiriti o Waitangi that caused harm to Ngāti Hāua.
“A key component of the Deed is Te Tātairango o Te Karauna – a collective agreement, between Ngāti Hāua and key Crown agencies to support, resource and empower the future wellbeing of the Iwi.”
The redress package agreed on today includes:

the return of 64 culturally significant sites including Ngā Huinga (Cherry Grove) where the Whanganui and Taringamotu Rivers meet.
a $6-million cultural revitalisation fund
$19 million of financial redress
statutory pardons for two Ngāti Hāua ancestors who were tried under martial law and treated with exceptional harshness. One was confined for life and the other was sentenced to death.

“While no settlement can fully compensate for the Crown’s injustices towards Ngāti Hāua, I sincerely hope this redress package will support Ngāti Hāua to realise their economic and cultural aspirations for generations to come,” says Mr Goldsmith.
Ngāti Hāua is a tribe based in the Central North Island, centred in Taumarunui. They have a population of approximately 2,500 members.
A copy of the Deed of Settlement is available online at: Te Tari Whakatau - Ngāti Hāua
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 29 Mar 2025 14:20:51 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124710</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Employment Relations Authority members sought</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/employment-relations-authority-members-sought</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Workplace Relations and Safety Minister Brooke van Velden is seeking new members to fill multiple vacancies at the Employment Relations Authority (ERA) as several existing members have not been reappointed.
The ERA is an independent body that helps resolve employment relationship problems and facilitates collective bargaining when issues arise.&nbsp;
“ERA members have an important role to play in supporting both worker and employer certainty and ensuring employers and employees do right by each other. It is important the ERA attracts committed and experienced people who can arrive at sound and reasonable decisions on employment law matters,” says Ms van Velden.&nbsp;
“There are five upcoming vacancies, and I am encouraging expressions of interest from candidates who understand the expectations, realities and demands of New Zealand’s various workplaces.
“Much of my policy work programme is aimed at restoring certainty for all parties, for example by removing eligibility for remedies if the employee is at fault. I want to ensure that decisions made by the ERA inspire certainty in workplaces as well, which requires that the right people are appointed.
“I note the experience and backgrounds of ERA members has been unbalanced. Currently, 76 per cent of ERA members have significant experience in the public sector, but only 48 percent in private business. I would like to see the make-up of ERA membership better reflect the proportions of public sector and private sector employment in New Zealand.
“By having employment disputes resolved quickly we can ease the burden on New Zealand’s court system. It also means the parties involved will not need to waste as much time and money on trying to sort out work-related problems they may be experiencing.
“This Government is committed to supporting thriving and productive workplaces. ERA decisions can have a material impact on the costs of being an employer and doing business and can impact workers’ confidence to enter or remain in the workforce,” says Ms van Velden.&nbsp;
Applicants will ideally be experienced in employment law or business and be adept at getting to the core of a problem and finding fair and equitable solutions. They can be based in either Christchurch, Wellington or Auckland.
Applications can be made on the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment website:&nbsp;Employment Relations Authority Member Job Details | MBIEPROD.
The application process closes on 20 April 2025.&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 16:26:52 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124709</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Speech to NZ Planning Institute Conference</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/speech-nz-planning-institute-conference</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Introduction
Thank you for inviting me to speak with you today about the new resource management system the Government is introducing, starting this year. I want to acknowledge Hon Rachel Brooking, opposition spokesperson for RMA Reform, as well as Simon Court, my Under-Secretary, who I will invite to speak after me.
I would like to acknowledge the NZPI, David and Andrea, and the many planners here today, as key and influential players as the Government takes action to replace the Resource Management Act.
You, more than most, will understand the frustration and headwinds that the RMA has caused for everyone involved in the system – from applicants just wanting to get things done, to councils trying to implement and administer the RMA, to planners such as yourselves, and other experts, who are trying to do their best within what is a fundamentally broken system.
I am concerned that the social license of planning is at risk, with some seeing planners as stifling development rather than enabling it.
I accept that you have been working and operating in an uncertain and broken system. A system that encourages too much consultation and too much regulation for fear of landing yourselves court.
We are fixing the planning system. We are doing our part to improve the system, which means you have to do your part, too.
You have to properly balance the protection of the environment with the necessity of development, accepting that things like houses, supermarkets, and quarries are not nice to haves: they are essentials for human life.
We live in a free market economy, and not a planned one. Commerce and trade must happen, and it isn’t the job of the planning system to control or prevent those things.
You all have a critical role to play in New Zealand’s growth journey. We are a country that has been living beyond our means for too long – with an economy our size, that is thirsty for growth, we cannot justify being as restrictive and fragmented as we have been.
As a country, we have to start saying ‘yes’ a lot more, and ‘no’ a lot less. We have accepted our part we play in helping you do that, and I look forward to working with you on the part you need to play as well.
I know the NZPI has thousands of members and a long proud history of providing good advice and advocacy and I look forward to working with you on the replacement for the RMA.
As you know, earlier this week, Cabinet took decisions on a new resource management system. We’ve made some announcements including sharing the Expert Advisory Group report and recommendations, which I have heard has contributed to healthy discussion and debate at your yearly conference down here in Invercargill.
The need for reform
As you know more than most, the RMA is broken and is a handbrake on growth for the country and you can directly trace the onset of our housing affordability crisis to the introduction of the RMA.
It’s also too hard to build renewable energy, it’s too hard to get a road or quarry consented, it’s too hard to get roads built, it’s too hard to do anything.
That’s why it’s critical that over the next two years and beyond, we nail resource management reform.
The Government is committed to reforming the resource management system to drive economic growth and increase productivity by making it easier to get things done in New Zealand.
Our intention is to replace the Resource Management Act with two new acts – one to focus on land-use planning and the second to focus on the natural environment.
The new system will provide a framework that makes it easier to plan and deliver infrastructure as well as protecting the environment. But before I share further detail, I’d like to cover the significant progress we have made already.
As you will be aware, we have taken a phased approach to resource management reform.
Our first phase of resource management reform was the repeal of the Natural and Built Environment Act and Spatial Planning Act in December 2023.
The second phase was to deliver targeted changes to the RMA through two amendment bills, focused on relieving the most significant resource management issues in the short term, as well as fast-track and changes to the suite of national direction.
In October 2024, the first RMA Amendment Bill, came into force. This sought to reduce the regulatory burden on resource consent applicants as well as supporting development in key sectors, including farming and other primary industries.
In December the Fast-track Approvals Bill was enacted, and from February it has been open for referral and substantive applications.
The second of the RMA bills is now before the Environment Select Committee – and is a precursor to full replacement of the Resource Management Act. This Bill will make important changes in the short term to make it quicker and simpler to consent renewable energy, boost housing supply, and reduce red tape. The Select Committee is due to report back in June on this Bill.
Phase three
The third and final phase of the resource management reform programme is the full replacement of the RMA.
Last year, we established the Expert Advisory Group, ably led by Janette Campbell to develop a blueprint for replacing the resource management legislation. The Expert Advisory Group worked at pace, and I would like to congratulate Janette and the Group on the quality of the report and appreciate all their efforts in the later part of last year to deliver the Blueprint.
At the commencement of the reform process, Cabinet set 10 principles for the Expert Advisory Group to consider in the development of the Blueprint. The EAG report provides a broadly workable basis for the new resource management system, and the report has guided Cabinet decision-making on the broad architecture.
I say broadly workable – it is of course obvious to everyone in this room that with any planning system the devil is in the detail, and we do have more work to do.
Today I want to take you through the ten principles Cabinet asked the EAG to ‘build out’, and how they are being carried forward into the next system.
Narrow the scope of the system
The first of these principles was to narrow the scope of the resource management system and the effects it controls. The RMA right now just does far too much.
When you’re trying to manage for everything, often, you achieve nothing.
The new system will have a narrower approach to effects management based on the economic concept of externalities. Effects that are borne solely by the party undertaking the activity will not be controlled, while financial or competitive matters will be excluded.
For example, under the new system you will be able to change the interior or exterior of a building, which have no impact on neighbours, such as the size or configuration of apartments, the provision of balconies, as well as outdoor open spaces for a private dwelling.
The new legislation will narrow the scope of system, with the enjoyment of property rights as the guiding principle.
Now a lot of people are getting quite worked up about this. People often get obsessed about whether or not something is or is not a human right – and I must admit that a pet peeve of mine is the overuse of this label.
But something that is actually contained in the United Nations Declaration of Human Rights is that “no one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his property”.
When people are stopped from doing what they want on their own property, for no good reason, then in my view: that is arbitrarily depriving them of their property.
We have been very clear that the new system will protect property rights, so long as you are not impacting others. To be even clearer: I see protection of the environment as a fundamental feature of any regime built on these ideals.
Respecting private property rights within the framework of a market economy, while also protecting the environment is exactly what we will do.
Compared to the RMA, the new legislation will more clearly define the types of adverse effects that can be considered and raise the threshold for when those adverse effects must be managed.
This will be a significant transformation of New Zealand’s resource management system and marks a shift from aprecautionary to a more permissive approach.
Both Acts will include starting presumptions that a land use is enabled, unless there is a significant enough impact on either the ability of others to use their own land or on the natural environment. This will reduce the scope of effects being regulated and enable more activities to take place as of right.
There will be a requirement for regulatory justification reports if departing from approaches to regulation standardised at the national level.
Subject to further detailed design advice, the legislation will also include protection against regulatory takings. This will allow affected landowners to seek recourse where it is found that unjustified restrictions placed on them.
We are also proposing a smaller number of consent categories that will make it simpler and more certain for applicants.
This includes removing non-complying activities.
8-10% of all resource consent applications every year are for non-complying activities. The gateway test in the RMA, creates a barrier to development even when applicants do everything they can to mitigate effects.
One point that I wanted to make today was in regards to the effects threshold, or the materiality of effects that is addressed by our resource management system. The RMA has led to a system that accounts for and address all effects, with only ‘de minimus’ effects discounted.
The EAG recommended lifting the threshold to ‘minor’ or ‘more than minor’ adverse effects, meaning that land-use is enabled, unless there are minor or more than minor effects on either the ability of others to use their land (in the Planning Act) or on the natural environment in the NEA.
The EAG point out that the RMA requires less than minor effects to be considered, including for who is involved in consenting processes i.e. who may be affected or whether a consent is publicly notified.
Cabinet has agreed to ‘raise the threshold for the level of adverse effects on people and the environment that can be considered in setting rules and determining who is affected by a resource consent’.
We liked where the EAG was going, but we want to take a look at this to make sure that we have the settings right, and that what we do will avoid as much as possible 30 years of litigation about what the proper definition of the thresholds are.
This has a real impact on how people interact and use the resource management system, and how decisions are made, so we do need to do further work here and I look forward to feedback on where we land.
Establish two Acts with clear and distinct purposes
The second principle was to establish two Acts with clear and distinct purposes, one to manage environmental effects arising from activities and another to enable urban development and infrastructure.
Cabinet has now recommitted to this, and can confirm that the new planning system will be made up of two new Acts.
The first act – The Planning Act – will focus on planning and regulating the use, development and enjoyment of land.
It will enable the urban and infrastructure development New Zealand needs and will align with the Government’s Going for Housing Growth plan and 30-year National Infrastructure Plan.
The second act – The Natural Environment Act – will focus on the use, protection, and enhancement of the natural environment. This includes our land, air, freshwater, coastal and marine water, and other natural resources.
Our natural resource management needs a clearer focus on what matters most in regulating the use, protection and enhancement of the environment.
Cabinet has accepted the EAG’s recommendation for only one set of national direction under each act.
National Direction under the Natural Environment Act will cover freshwater, indigenous biodiversity and coastal policy.
National Direction under the new Planning Act will cover urban development, infrastructure – including renewable energy – and natural hazards.&nbsp;
Strengthen the role of environmental limits
The third principle was to strengthen and clarify the role of environmental limits and how they are to be developed.
For environmental limits there will be a clearer legislative basis for setting them for our natural environment. This will provide more certainty around where development can and should be enabled, whilst protecting the environment.
Like I mentioned earlier, things like houses, supermarkets, and quarries are essential to any modern country. They actually aren’t nice to haves – they are must haves. A regime of environmental limits ensures that everyone’s obligations are clear, and developers have understood safe harbours to operate within.
While local variation will still be possible, designing the system around default pathways like this will provide greater investment certainty, and improve the timeliness of decision-making.
National standards
And that nicely brings me to the fourth principle, to provide for greater use of national standards to reduce the need for resource consents and to simplify council plans, so that standard-complying activity cannot be subjected to a consent requirement.
Nationally set standards, including standardised land use zones, will provide significant system benefits and efficiencies. The new legislation will provide for greater standardisation and ensure that policy setting happens at the national level, while local decision is enabled for the things that matter.
New Zealand does not need 1175 different types of zones. In Japan, which uses standardised planning, they have only 13 zones.
Standardised zones will significantly reduce the cost of plan development borne by councils.
Across New Zealand local government incurs costs of $90 million per year, developing consulting and implementing regional and district plans.
Under the new system, council costs for developing their own zones, definitions, policies, objectives, rules and overlays will significantly reduce, as these would be set at the national level. They will focus on where the zones developed by central government will apply, and develop bespoke zones, if needed.
An economic analysis of the EAG report estimated a halving in the overall costs of plan making and implementation, across the country. This could save an estimated $14.8 billion in council administrative and compliance costs, over a 30-year period.
A standardised system will also provide much more consistency for users working across multiple local government borders, a benefit that should not be underestimated. Inconsistent rules cause frustration and added cost for resource consent applicants who have to redo otherwise identical proposals to match local plan requirements.
In addition to cost savings, standardised zones will be more flexible and permissive than many of the zones applied by local councils. This will improve economic efficiency and provide more choice for businesses and consumers. I would expect, for example, this to help drive down the cost of building a house.
We will be looking to international examples of standardised zones. While we hope to go somewhat further in terms of standardisation than some of the Australian states have done, they provide a useful cross reference for us. Victoria replaced 2,870 zones with 25 standardised zones which enable a wider range of land uses and development.
Resource consents will still be needed under the new system, but with the new nationally standardized land use zones and more national standards, there will be much fewer resource consents required and more permitted activities.
Compliance monitoring and enforcement
The fifth principle was the agreement that the new system would see a shift from consenting before any works are undertaken, to strengthened compliance monitoring and enforcement after the activity. 
We are acutely aware that if we truly want an enduring system that is enabling of development, we need to show Kiwis that this can exist at the same time as good environmental protection.
All users of the system need to be aware that while we will be enabling them, we expect them to follow the rules. And if they don’t, there will be consequences.
The new system will improve the consistency and strength of environmental monitoring and enforcement. This will ensure that whilst the new system will be more enabling, the rules for environmental protection will be clear and consistent across the country, and anyone seen to be flouting the rules will be more likely to have enforcement action taken against them.
This work will involve consideration of an entity like the Environmental Protection Authority to perform compliance and enforcement functions, and environmental monitoring functions centrally, removing these functions from councils.
This will be done in a separate legislative process and is not part of the two new Acts.
This, combined with other system changes (ie, national standards and zones) would involve a reduction in the role of local government which if progressed, could have wider implications for the structure of local government in New Zealand. The Minister of Local Government and I are working through these issues now, and expect to have more to say later this year.
Council plans
Each Act will require one combined plan per region – including spatial planning – with plan chapters being developed by each local authority, combined for each region, then presented as a national e-plan as per Cabinet principles six and seven.
This will result in a smaller number of plans overall, that will be simpler to use, and consistent across the country.
Spatial planning done right will enable housing and business development in places where constraints can be avoided or appropriately managed, as well as support early protection of infrastructure corridors and strategic sites, lowering the cost of infrastructure.
Cabinet has also agreed to establish a new planning tribunal for low-cost dispute resolution, as per the eight principle.
Uphold Treaty of Waitangi settlements
Critically, the ninth principle was to uphold Treaty settlements and the crowns obligations.
In the last few days, some people have been mischaracterising the Government's position by saying there would be no treaty clause at all in the new planning system. This is untrue.
As per our coalition agreements, there will not be a generic Treaty clause that says that the act must give effect to or take account of the principles of the Treaty of Waitangi. The Government’s intent is that there will be a descriptive clause instead, that will recognise the Treaty of Waitangi and the uniqueness of the settlements entered into by Iwi with the Crown.
The problem with generic treaty principles clauses is they are open ended and amorphous, and they create uncertainty and legal risk for everybody. There is an opportunity through the development of more descriptive treaty clauses to really spell out everyone's specific roles in the new system.
This may include refreshing provisions that provide for Māori participation in the RMA, making sure they are relevant in modern New Zealand and are achieving their underlying purpose.
We will also work with post-settlement governance entities to ensure that historical Treaty settlements and other arrangements, including rights acknowledged under Takutai Moana legislation, are upheld.
It is a bottom line for this government that we uphold and honour Treaty settlements that the Crown has entered into in good faith, and this includes in these reforms.
Having outlined the above nine principles, I hope you can agree that principle ten has clearly been achieved, which was to provide faster, cheaper and less litigious processes within shorter, less complex and more accessible legislation.
As I have said: the devil will be in the detail, and there is still water to go under the bridge. But with the EAG’s blueprint, I feel confident that we are going to get this done, achieving better outcomes for all New Zealanders.
Changes to Phase 2 national direction programme
Now those eagled-eyed viewers of government policy will remember the Government has an ambitious plan in Phase 2 of our reforms to update and modernize a series of National Direction to ensure New Zealanders experience gains in the short term from a more enabling system.
Our previously announced national direction program included 21 instruments, which collectively would have substantial implementation requirements of local government.
In light of the significance of the phase 3 reform, the Government has decided to relook at our Phase 2 national direction program and focus it to deliver on Government priorities while minimizing disruption to the resource management system.
Today I am confirming that we will still be progressing most of what was previously announced.
As promised, the planned freshwater package will continue, as well as changes to both national policy statements (known as NPSs) and national environmental standards (known as NESs).
Specifically: for freshwater – the package will include amendments to the NPS-Freshwater Management, NES for freshwater, the stock exclusion regulations, drinking water proposals and enabling vegetable growing and water storage.
In fact, all NES proposals will continue as planned. This includes new national standards on granny flats, pakakāinga, and amendments to existing standards on electricity transmission, telecoms, aquaculture, and commercial forestry.
Targeted changes to selected national policy statements (NPSs) will also continue, and will have immediate effect to support better decision making on the ground.
These include more enabling policies in the NPS Infrastructure, NPS-Renewable Electricity Generation, NPS-Electricity Transmission and the New Zealand Coastal Policy Statement.
Also as promised, we will also be progressing quarrying and mining consistency changes across NPS-Freshwater Management, NPS-Indigenous Biodiversity and NPS-Highly Productive Land.
We will do a narrow change to the NPS-Highly Productive Land - to remove Land Use Capability (LUC) class 3 from the definition of highly productive land, to help support cities expand but still protect key soils under LUC 1 and 2.
And finally a scaled back national direction on managing natural hazard risk to support councils managing significant risk from hazards.
Some of you may be disappointed that we aren’t progressing some policies, for example changes to the effects management hierarchy for things like electricity and infrastructure development, as well as more substantial changes to things like the NPS-Indigenous Biodiversity, and some changes to the NPS-Urban Development.
Last year I announced changes we intended to progress on the NPS-Urban Development. We are committed to progressing housing growth targets and strengthening density requirements. But if we made changes now to the NPS-UD, this would require councils undertaking substantive plan changes, which considering the new planning system will be up and running by 2027, forcing councils to undertake a costly and lengthy plan change now wasn’t really feasible.
So as part of the consultation on national direction we will include a package on housing and urban development, focused on how our proposals will port into the new system.
The new system provides opportunities to achieve greater urban outcomes, through standardized zones and spatial planning, so this is a little short-term pain for massive long-term gain.
I expect to release the detail of these changes in the next 2 months, and have them in place by the end of the year.
Conclusion
We’re acutely conscious that the Government is moving fast and we’re making a lot of changes to resource management law.
But we want to settle on a system that is enduring, so that we can get on with implementing it.
The Government wants a rapid transition to the new system.
Our intention is that both new acts are put in place together, along with prioritised sets of new national direction, as I outlined earlier.
We anticipate turning on the new system at a fixed date, rather than the 10-year timeframe under the previous Government’s reforms. Local government entities are expected to be able to begin implementing the new system from 2027.
We also recognize that in order to transition quickly to the new system, with minimal disruption, local government and others in the system will require implementation support, which we have started work on already.
What we are doing is difficult and complicated, but it will create a more enabling framework, one that protects the environment and sets environmental bottom lines.
As members of the planning community, you have a huge part to play in providing feedback and ideas on how the new system can work, along with supporting councils and others with implementation.
We need a resource management system that will help drive economic growth and increase productivity by making it easier to get things done in New Zealand.
I look forward to your feedback and to discussing your ideas, as we continue to create a better resource management system for everyone.
Thank you for the opportunity to speak with you today. I will now hand over to my Under-Secretary, Simon Court, who is assisting me with these reforms.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 15:04:47 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124708</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Speech to NZ Planning Institute Conference 2025</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/speech-nz-planning-institute-conference-2025</link>
  <description><![CDATA[It’s great to be here today on what has been a momentous week for resource management reform.
As you’ve heard, Minister Bishop and I have been working hard to reset resource management in New Zealand.
Today I want to talk to you about the broader step change and what that is going to mean.
Among the many problems the RMA has caused is a playing field of skewed incentives for decision makers that has led to a culture of risk aversion and restriction.
As policy makers, we must expect people to follow the incentives they face. That is rational.
This is why it is important our reforms get the incentives right, to minimise distortion and incentivise optimal outcomes.
There are several elements of the reform that are particularly important in achieving this; in transforming this culture of planners first saying “no, but…” to one of “yes, and...” We must do away this culture of regulatory anxiety.
Regulatory anxiety
Good decisions rest on benefits outweighing costs, and on decision-makers facing the right incentives to adequately assess these costs and benefits in full.
Yet, planners working under the RMA are trapped in an asymmetric system.
The risks of saying yes—public backlash, political fallout, legal challenge and cost—are much more direct and salient to those making the decisions.&nbsp;
The costs of excessive caution—housing shortages, infrastructure deficits, wasted economic opportunity, and infringements on people’s property rights—not so much.
Many of these costs are spread across society and felt over decades, some just shovelled onto private property owners to cop. This system rewards planners for avoiding risk, not for enabling growth, and it enables the undermining of property rights in the process.
The result? A culture of “no” and a bias toward excessive caution; caution that ties us down and squanders the great opportunity we have to cement our spot as the best country on the planet.
We’re making several moves to drive change.
Fixing the problem
Descoping
I have been beating the drum about the RMA’s absurdly broad scope for a while now, and we’ve talked about descoping as principle number one of the reform, so I will spare you the further noise beyond saying this: descoping the ‘effects’ the system manages will play a core role in liberating planners from the regulatory anxiety with respect to so many things currently managed.&nbsp;
There will simply be less to do, and less to worry about.
The right to plan
The reforms will reinforce that districts and cities have the right to plan. Your city, your district, will have democratic accountability for choosing where to grow from standardised zones set at a national level, providing a high level of regulatory assurance to planners.
By closing the door to anyone who doesn’t like their specific height to boundary ratio to agitate for some bespoke zoning rules, this will necessarily ease pressure facing planners who currently must defend these things.
Communities will still get to have their say at the planning phase—and, in fact, they will be incentivised to do so—but we do intend for the ability for appeals to be greatly reduced which will go a long way toward reducing regulatory anxiety. This is an area we will firm up over the coming months.
National standards for common activities
Similarly, national standards for common activities will reduce anxiety that planners and decision makers currently have when it comes to forming up defensible consent conditions for what are relatively common and necessary activities.
Under the current system, decision makers must assess a wide range of potential effects, which often drives disproportionality between the consent conditions and the effect they are trying to manage, for the sake of appeasing noisy NIMBYs who don’t like things like quarrying, and who may be motivated to appeal otherwise reasonable decisions.
This often leads to a “ratcheting up” effect on consent conditions in an attempt by both applicants and decision makers to ward off pesky appeals.&nbsp;
Codifying practice for common activities, like earthworks and working in a water course, into regular standards will liberate the anxiety planners face to set ever more stringent conditions and give development a mandate to certainly and sensibly occur, from Cape Reinga to Bluff.
Environment
The current system presumes that developers and infrastructure must avoid sensitive environments and that only by a torturous and often litigious process can an outcome which benefits the environment overall be arrived at.
Instead of spending weeks and months and years and tens of millions of dollars arguing with any Tom, Dick or Harry in various hearings, wouldn’t it be better that experts direct their energy into win-wins? Biodiversity offsetting springs to mind as a particular area of opportunity to help deliver both better development and environmental results.
Offsetting and compensation should be a starting point for conversations beginning with “yes, and”, because for someone like me who thinks an ideal date is an eco-adventure to see creatures like lizards, bats, and Freddie the frog, that could equally be a constructed wetland at an active or rehabilitated mine site, as much as it could be to Zealandia.&nbsp;
Planning Tribunal
While these anxiety-reducing steps we’re taking will go some way to restoring balance and proportionality in decisions, there is a need for additional tension in the system to offset the distortion towards regulatory overreach and too much “no” in planning and decision-making.
This is a key focus of the Planning Tribunal.
By providing an accountability mechanism against scope creep and unjustified regulation, the Planning Tribunal will provide the tension in the system necessary to ensure the system is delivering as intended.
No longer will it be the easy way out to default into decision making that appeases salient interests and pressures at the expense of growth and progress.
Compensation for takings
Further tension will be introduced through compensation for regulatory takings to ensure decision makers are confronted with the costs of decisions to infringe on property rights.
Morally, it is simply not fair to force people to privately cop the cost of decisions supposedly made in the public interest—if the public has an interest, the public should pay.
Compensation for regulatory takings is akin to a congestion charge on regulation.&nbsp;
Without a price on congestion, there is too much traffic. Without a price on protecting trees, or ‘outstanding’ or ‘highly productive’ land, there is a risk of too much regulation on people who want nothing to do with it.
We pay people for their losses from compulsory acquisition under the Public Works Act, and there’s no reason the same principle should not apply for partial takings for the public good under resource management legislation.
Moral case aside, this will lead to more careful consideration with respect to decisions that would restrict property rights, and ensure they occur only where there is a genuine net public good.
Conclusion
We are clear on the problems we intend to solve through the new planning system for people and the environment.
We are clear this requires a culture change.
We are clear that this culture change rests on a reset of the incentives for decision makers.
This requires a fundamental shift in the values and behaviours of the planning workforce which must align with our nation’s ambitions for the new system.&nbsp;
A culture change means planners and decision makers share the ambition of property owners to maximise enjoyment of their property, of developers to deliver affordable homes, and of the infrastructure guardians to provide efficient and safe infrastructure.
To enhance overall performance, a culture change from “no, but” to ”yes, and” is a must-have, not a nice to have.
The new system will be designed to enable this culture change, and to enforce it where old habits persist.
I look forward to working with planning professionals on this necessary evolution.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 14:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124707</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Improved hunting permit system on its way </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/improved-hunting-permit-system-its-way</link>
  <description><![CDATA[A new and improved hunting permit system will make it easier for New Zealanders to go hunting on public conservation land Minister for Hunting and Fishing James Meager says.
“Longer permits, automatic reminders and better navigation are part of a significant upgrade that will make life easier for 34,000 hunters that hunt on open conservation land,” Minister Meager says.
“The underlying technology of the current hunting permit system is outdated and in need of an update, and is being improved based on the direct feedback of hunters. This upgrade will support more hunters, both domestic and international, getting out and doing what they love.
“This substantial upgrade to the permitting system will make it more reliable and easier to navigate on mobile devices, making it easier to obtain permits on the go. Hunting permits will now be valid for 12 months, an increase on the current four-month period. Hunters will also receive reminders 14 days before their permits are due to expire so they can easily obtain a new permit.&nbsp;
“The upgraded system will also make selecting hunting areas easier. Instead of the 54 hunting areas that hunters currently choose from, the system will be simplified so hunters choose from eight regions, four in the North Island and four in the South Island/Stewart Island. All existing hunting areas within the broader region will automatically be included on the permit, and hunters can also select all hunting areas within New Zealand at the press of a single button.
“These may be simple changes, but they reflect a government which is committed to making it easier for New Zealanders to go hunting and fishing on conservation land, and are willing to listen to the feedback of the hunting community to do so.”
This new system will be launched by the Department in Conservation in May.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 13:45:32 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124706</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>New mobile dental clinic will reach thousands of children</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/new-mobile-dental-clinic-will-reach-thousands-children</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Heath Minister Simeon Brown has today launched a new mobile dental clinic in South Auckland, increasing access to dental care for the local community.
“Ensuring all children have access to timely, quality healthcare is a priority for the Government.
“Expanding dental services and offering early access to oral healthcare, close to home, is key to improving overall oral health.
“About 50 per cent of children waiting for dental care in the Auckland region live in the Counties Manukau area.
“This purpose-built, mobile clinic will provide dental assessments, treatment, and oral health education for up to 3,000 children each year.&nbsp;
“By taking these services directly to local neighbourhoods and community events, we can address many of the barriers that prevent children from receiving appropriate oral healthcare in a timely manner.
“Early access and education are key to preventing a number of dental issues and reducing the chance of children needing treatment under anaesthetic in hospital.
“I know how important it is to set children up early for a healthy future, which is why initiatives that provide community care in a setting closer to home are so important.
“I’m pleased for the thousands of children who will be able to benefit from this mobile dental clinic in the future, ensuring timely and quality access to oral healthcare for the South Auckland community,” Mr Brown says.&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 12:20:51 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124704</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>New Zealand 3D maps are a game-changer</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/new-zealand-3d-maps-are-game-changer</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Most of New Zealand has now been mapped in 3D, creating a rich dataset for planning economic growth, land management and modelling for risk, Land Information Minister Chris Penk and Associate Regional Development Minister Mark Patterson say.
“New Zealand’s landscape is constantly evolving, and it’s crucial that we understand how,” Mr Penk says.
“For the first time, this information is available as a single, comprehensive national dataset. With 80 percent of New Zealand now mapped, we can analyse most of the country at once, rather than taking a fragmented region-by-region approach. This has enormous value for decision-making, planning, and modelling.
“LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) data provides a baseline for tracking geological and geographical changes over time, from natural events such as erosion and shifting river paths to new manmade developments.
“It’s an essential tool for councils to better manage natural hazards by modelling flood zones, identifying slip-prone land and creating hazard maps to help keep people safe. We can also quickly collect new data after natural disasters to assess the impact, which will support recovery efforts.”
The PGF-LiDAR programme and the 10 regional councils who co-funded the project were supported by $14.6 million in grants from the former Provincial Growth Fund, administered by Kānoa - Regional Economic Development &amp; Investment Unit.
“The 3D maps enable smarter planning and investment in regional forestry planting operations and greater agricultural productivity,” Mr Patterson says.
“Councils are applying the data to ecosystem services such as runoff and nutrient retention, shade and ultraviolet protection, and landscape aesthetics.
“Councils may also use the data for compliance monitoring such as identification of excessive earthworks and quarrying, tree removal, or building activity across the regions.”
The data was captured by aircraft fitted with LiDAR technology, which uses pulsed light to measure the distance from the plane to the land below to build up a 3D picture of the country - accurate down to the nearest metre.
A new partnership with Ngā Tāngata Tiaki o Whanganui will contribute LiDAR data for the entire Whanganui River catchment, which will be available later this year.
Note to editors:
LINZ administered the LiDAR funding and makes the data available for free on the LINZ Data Service website.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 11:52:06 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124703</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Innovation drives refreshed disability strategy </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/innovation-drives-refreshed-disability-strategy</link>
  <description><![CDATA[New Zealand’s strategy to improve the lives and uphold the rights of disabled people will be refreshed using an innovative new approach, Disability Issues Minister Louise Upston has announced.
“The current 10-year strategy ends in 2026 and has provided a valuable focus for disability work during the past decade,” Louise Upston says.&nbsp;
“While progress has been made, there is clearly more to do.
“We’re going to tackle the next refresh in a new way. In a New Zealand first, working groups drawn from the disabled community, industry and government agencies will develop actions in key focus areas. The draft strategy will then go to the wider disabled community for further review before being agreed.
“The resulting document will endure for five years, focusing on key areas where differences can be made for disabled people including education, employment, health, housing and justice.
“This is an exciting opportunity. The Ministry of Disabled People - Whaikaha is managing the refresh process, and has received almost 350 expressions of interest from disabled people keen to take part.
“Recent data from the Stats NZ Household Disability Survey found disabled New Zealanders continue to face many barriers, for example in education, employment and housing.
“We know 1 in 6 New Zealanders are disabled, yet three quarters of unemployed disabled people want to be working which means creating employment opportunities must be an important focus.&nbsp;
“Disabled people, like non-disabled people, want to participate in their communities, to thrive and make decisions about their own lives.
“There will be challenges ahead as the refresh proceeds, but equally there are also huge opportunities to make a positive difference,” Louise Upston says.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 11:00:07 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124702</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Government addresses Wellington Water concerns</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/government-addresses-wellington-water-concerns</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is accelerating Local Water Done Well for the Wellington region to provide greater transparency at Wellington Water and ensure it is delivering value for money for ratepayers, say Local Government Minister Simon Watts and Commerce and Consumer Affairs Minister Scott Simpson.
“Over the last few months, I have had serious concerns around Wellington’s water services,” Mr Watts says.
“Recent reports have shone a spotlight on high costs and unsound financial management at Wellington Water with clear evidence suggesting the ratepayers are not getting good value for money,” Mr Watts says.
“I am not satisfied by the progress made to address these glaring problems and without clear and decisive action, Wellingtonians face a decade of hefty rate increases with little to show for it.”
The Government is bringing forward Local Water Done Well for the Wellington region by imposing early economic regulation on Wellington Water. This means the Commerce Commission will begin its role as a monitor for the Wellington region’s water services sooner than other water services under Local Water Done Well.
“Given the current issues, Wellingtonians shouldn’t have to wait for the full economic regulation regime to be in place to have greater visibility over how their money is spent on water services,” Mr Simpson says.
“The Commission will impose foundational information disclosure requirements on Wellington Water. This will require it to report to the public and the Commission on key delivery performance and financial management measures.
“While the precise disclosure requirements will be set by the Commission, we anticipate it will include indicators that provide a view of value for money, procurement practices, and plans to address the shortcomings outlined in the published reports.”
Mr Watts says the action today to increase public accountability at Wellington Water is implemented under Local Water Done Well legislation the Coalition Government passed last year.
“The purpose of economic regulation including information disclosures is to promote the long-term benefit of consumers of water services and to ensure that sufficient information is available to assess whether that is occurring.
“The foundational information disclosure framework provided for under last year’s Local Government (Water Services Preliminary Arrangements) Act means we can ensure a more detailed picture sooner of how Wellington Water intends to address performance shortfalls in key areas.
“Experience in other sectors shows information disclosure provides greater transparency and is expected to drive a shift in organisational behaviour. The action we are taking will help ensure steps are taken to reduce unnecessary future costs for Wellington ratepayers.
“This is consistent with the Government’s Local Water Done Well objectives – financially sustainable water services with strong regulatory oversight, strict rules for water quality and ongoing investment. It is also consistent with our focus on tackling cost of living challenges for New Zealanders.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 11:02:45 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124701</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title> Wildlife Act fix will enable economic growth with animal protection</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/wildlife-act-fix-will-enable-economic-growth-animal-protection</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Prompt improvements to the Wildlife Act will ensure infrastructure developments and important conservation work can continue supporting our growing economy while protecting our precious wildlife, Conservation Minister Tama Potaka says.
The High Court recently decided it was unlawful for the Department of Conservation – Te Papa Atawhai to authorise the New Zealand Transport Agency – Waka Kotahi under section 53 of the Wildlife Act to harm protected wildlife species while building the Mt Messenger highway.
“As permission was also granted under another section of the Act, the court’s decision doesn’t affect this highway’s ongoing construction. It will not affect Fast Track projects either,” Mr Potaka says.
“However, the decision could delay other projects DOC has given permission for or are still coming through the pipeline under section 53 of the Act – such as building new solar and wind farms, plantation forests, and powerline maintenance that are essential for supporting our growing economy. It also affects other important conservation work, like pest control.
"The Government intends to promptly change the law to enable these important activities to go ahead lawfully, including the building of houses and roads for example, as they have in the past with safeguards for wildlife. These amendments will provide certainty for existing projects,” Mr Potaka says.
“While developers are absolutely expected to make the best possible effort to protect our precious wildlife when getting on with their mahi, they should have confidence they won’t be prosecuted if their projects incidentally kill protected wildlife despite having previous authorisation and complying with the conditions set.&nbsp;
“It’s important Aotearoa New Zealand’s wildlife continues to be protected and that species can thrive as we support a strong and growing economy. The Government still expects responsible developers to seek permission for the activities they undertake – for example, seeking to relocate animals before doing any construction work – to protect populations and support the ongoing viability of species.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 09:06:22 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124700</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Reducing red tape to put patients first</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/reducing-red-tape-put-patients-first</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is reviewing New Zealand’s health workforce legislation to ensure the focus is on putting patients first, Health Minister Simeon Brown says.
Reviewing health workforce legislation will consider a number of key matters including:

Prioritising patient voices in regulatory decisions.
Reducing red tape to make healthcare more accessible.
Making it easier to recognise overseas regulations.
Driving efficiencies by streamlining regulatory decision making.

“We are committed to ensuring all New Zealanders can access timely, quality healthcare,” Mr Brown says.
“Making our health system more efficient and enabling frontline workers to get on with their jobs will allow it to become more responsive to patient needs.
“New Zealand’s current health workforce regulations can be overly bureaucratic, and this is slowing down access to care, increasing costs, and making it harder for patients to get the services they need.
“Our regulations can also make it harder to attract, train and retain healthcare workers. Whether it’s requiring nursing students to complete hundreds more clinical hours than those in Australia, complicated approval pathways for overseas qualified doctors to practice in NZ, or imposing rules that prioritise cultural requirements over clinical safety in scopes of practices, our healthcare system is being held back by outdated and unnecessary barriers.”
“We also need to better recognise overseas qualifications to speed up access to healthcare for patients. As part of the National-ACT Coalition agreement, we are also considering the establishment of an Occupations Tribunal which would consider appeals about decisions relating to overseas qualifications.
“Patients expect to receive care from qualified practitioners, with clinical safety as their top priority. Our proposals will also ensure that patients voices are heard in regulatory decision making, to ensure the needs of patients are considered when decisions are being made by regulatory bodies.
“We are also seeking feedback on how regulatory decisions can be made across all 18 health workforce regulatory bodies to ensure greater consistency. A streamlined system means more frontline staff available to provide care across the country, delivering shorter wait times and better health outcomes for all New Zealanders.”
Consultation has today opened on changes to the Health Practitioners Competence Assurance Act and the Government wants to hear from patients and our healthcare workers on how the regulatory system can better meet the needs of patients.
New Zealanders can submit their views on the Putting Patients First: Modernising Health Workforce Regulation document at www.health.govt.nz. Consultation closes on 30&nbsp;April 2025.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 08:41:14 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124699</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>More reliable, resilient supply vessel sought for Chatham Islands</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/more-reliable-resilient-supply-vessel-sought-chatham-islands</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is seeking proposals from shipping operators to provide a new supply vessel for the Chatham Islands, Associate Transport Minister James Meager announced today.&nbsp;
“The Government is committed to supporting Chatham Islanders,” Minister Meager says.
“The Chatham Islands’ current supply vessel, the Southern Tiare, is a vital economic lifeline for the community by carrying supplies to the island and livestock back to the mainland.&nbsp;
“However, at 39 years old, the vessel is older than I am, and unfortunately it is nearing the end of its life as a working vessel. It is frequently out of action for maintenance and repairs, causing significant hardship for the community. For example, recent crane failure on the Southern Tiare resulted in a fuel shortage on the islands, requiring rationing of petrol for local residents.”
“Today, the Government has opened tenders to shipping operators who can provide a more reliable and resilient shipping service to replace the Southern Tiare.&nbsp;The new service will need the capability to transport fuel, livestock and general freight to and from Waitangi Port and Pitt Island. Crucially, it will need to provide a regular, reliable and resilient service.”&nbsp;
“A Request for Proposals (RFP) published today on the Government Electronic Tender Service outlines our requirements in full detail.”
“In addition to finding a replacement vessel, we need to determine what improvements to existing port infrastructure are needed to support a new service. This will need to be considered alongside proposals received through the RFP process.”&nbsp;&nbsp;
“Last year, the Government sought information from suppliers who are potentially interested in providing shipping services. This gave us a solid understanding of the market’s capability to service the Chatham Islands’ unique requirements.”&nbsp;
The release of the RFP is the next step in the process and moves us closer to securing a replacement vessel that will service the community for many years to come.”
Go to&nbsp;https://www.gets.govt.nz/MT/ExternalTenderDetails.htm?id=31351880 for more information.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 15:11:11 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124697</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
