<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.beehive.govt.nz/">
  <channel>
    <title>Beehive.govt.nz - The official website of the New Zealand Government</title>
    <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/</link>
    <description/>
    <language>en</language>
    
    <item>
  <title>Modern civil aviation law comes into effect</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/modern-civil-aviation-law-comes-effect</link>
  <description><![CDATA[New Zealand’s new civil aviation law will modernise regulations and ensure New Zealanders are safe in our skies, Acting Transport Minister James Meager says.
“A strong aviation sector is integral to New Zealand’s economic success and to ensuring New Zealanders can get to where they need to go for work or leisure,” Mr Meager says.&nbsp;
“This Government is committed to supporting the aviation sector to grow and innovate. The new Civil Aviation Act, which comes into force today, focuses on keeping Kiwis safe while allowing for new technology and changing aviation needs. It will ensure we can keep pace with a rapidly changing aviation environment.
“A better and more robust process for authorising airline cooperation agreements will improve competition and ensure benefits for New Zealanders. Proposed decisions will be published and open for consultation before a final decision is made, ensuring transparency over the whole process. The new Act also provides the ability for more on-time performance reporting for airlines and price transparency mechanisms.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
“As remotely piloted aircraft, commonly referred to as drones, continue to develop, changes will also enable policies and rules to be updated more quickly, to encourage further innovation and investment.
“Aviation safety and security have also been boosted through random drug and alcohol testing being introduced for people involved in safety-sensitive work, and AvSec officers will have clearer powers to keep travellers safe.
“A new independent review function has also been introduced to enable individuals and organisations to seek expert independent reviews of decisions made by the Director of Civil Aviation, saving them significant time and money. This will enable a faster and more cost-effective alternative to going through the courts and will help ensure that our regulatory processes are fair and transparent. I expect to announce the names of the reviewers in the coming weeks.
“I know this legislation is something the aviation sector has been eagerly awaiting, and I thank them for their cooperation as the Act is implemented.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:56:02 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124762</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Super-sized granny flats coming to backyards</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/super-sized-granny-flats-coming-backyards</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Coalition Government will go even further than it earlier proposed to make it easier to build granny flats by increasing the maximum size allowed to be built without consents, say RMA Reform and Housing Minister Chris Bishop, Associate Finance Minister Shane Jones and Building and Construction Minister Chris Penk.&nbsp;
“It’s currently far too hard to build the homes New Zealanders need, with even the simplest dwellings tangling up homeowners and builders in red tape. That’s a big part of the reason why we’re replacing the Resource Management Act (RMA) with new laws based on property rights,” Mr Bishop says.&nbsp;
“At present, people who want to build a simple standalone dwelling on their properties need a building consent under the Building Act. In many cases, a resource consent under the Resource Management Act is required as well. These processes are complicated, time-consuming, and costly.&nbsp;
“Last year the Government consulted on allowing granny flats of up to 60 sq m to be built without building or resource consents. The proposal received huge support, and as a result the Government has agreed to go even further by increasing the maximum size to 70 sq m,” Mr Bishop says.&nbsp;
“Making it faster and more affordable to build granny flats provides families with more housing options, particularly for grandparents, people with disabilities, young adults and workers in the rural sector. We know increasing housing availability directly translates to lower living costs for our communities.&nbsp;&nbsp;
“A new National Environmental Standard (NES) under the RMA will be developed and in place by the end of this year to give effect to our proposals, timed to take effect with changes to the Building Act. This NES will require all councils to permit a granny flat on sites in rural and residential zones without the need to gain a resource consent.”&nbsp;
The move delivers on a New Zealand First-National coalition agreement to amend the Building Act and resource consenting system to make it easier to build granny flats.&nbsp;
“In the Far North I saw how extended family often live together at the same property. Changing the rules to make it easier to build more family accommodation allows generational living at an affordable price,” Mr Jones says.&nbsp;
“I am delighted to see this proposal come to fruition through this Government, which enables pragmatic solutions to problems which have previously been thought too difficult to solve.”&nbsp;
Mr Penk says the Government is laser-focused on making it easier for builders and all tradies to get on and do what they do best.&nbsp;
“Removing regulatory barriers and taking a commonsense approach to the consenting system is a critical part of increasing housing supply for Kiwis.&nbsp;
“The sector is vital to New Zealand, and we want to support its growth and productivity by doing all we can to get builders back on their tools, and out of the office by reducing their paperwork.”&nbsp;
The Government will introduce an amendment to the Building Act in the middle of this year which will exempt granny flats from needing a building consent if:&nbsp;&nbsp;

The granny flat has a simple design and meets the Building Code 
Building work is carried out by authorised building professionals&nbsp; 
Homeowners notify their local council before they commence building and once it is completed.&nbsp;

“We have carefully considered the feedback to make sure the path forward strikes the right balance between enabling housing growth and managing risks,” Mr Penk says.&nbsp;
“To support councils with local infrastructure funding for growing communities, the Government has agreed that infrastructure charges will continue to apply to granny flats through the Project Information Memorandum process.”&nbsp;Note to editors:

Public consultation ran from 17 June to 12 August 2024 and received a total of 1970 submissions.&nbsp; 
A summary of submissions was published in November 2024 and can be found on the MBIE website.&nbsp; 
The proposed consent exemption will not apply to any building work currently in progress or existing structures that fit the specifications of a granny flat under the final exemption criteria. It will apply only to granny flats built after the exemption is in force. 
Anyone who is unsure whether their building work needs a building or resource consent should check with their local council.&nbsp;


]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:09:53 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124761</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Ethnic Communities Minister outlines key priorities </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/ethnic-communities-minister-outlines-key-priorities</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Distinguished guests, community leaders, business representatives, and faith leaders.
It is my pleasure as the Minister for Ethnic Communities to address you today.&nbsp;
New Zealand is home to speakers of more than 170 languages, and while I would love to greet you in each one, for now let me extend a warm welcome to you all with a simple “Kia ora. Tēnā koutou, katoa.”
I would like to acknowledge and extend my gratitude to everyone here today.&nbsp; Your dedication and contributions continue to strengthen the fabric of our nation.
I also wish to thank those of you who have shared your insights and experiences, providing valuable perspectives on the opportunities and challenges facing New Zealand’s Ethnic Communities. Your input is critical in shaping policies and initiatives that reflect the needs of all New Zealanders.
It is a privilege to serve as the Minister for Ethnic Communities. When the Prime Minister invited me to take on this role, I was deeply honoured and excited by the opportunity to support and champion the diverse communities that make up our nation.
Almost one in four people in New Zealand belong to an Ethnic Community. In Auckland, that number rises to one in three. These communities contribute immeasurably to our country—bringing expertise, knowledge, and cultural vibrancy that enriches every aspect of New Zealand life.
I was fortunate enough to become Minister just in time to host the Lunar New Year event at Parliament, which was a vibrant and wonderful celebration.
And in a couple of days, I will be hosting Eid celebrations as well, and I look forward to recognising and celebrating the many other significant cultural events that unite our communities throughout the year.&nbsp;
Today, I would like to outline my priorities as your Minister and share my vision for how we can work together to achieve meaningful outcomes.&nbsp; I will get to that shortly.&nbsp; First, a bit about myself.&nbsp;
I bring my own experience to this role.&nbsp; I have lived in the Middle East, Asia and Africa. I have lived and worked in many communities sharing the challenges they faced and immersing myself in the culture and history of their countries.
I am constantly learning but my experience has helped me understand where our ethnic communities come from, what is important to them, some of the challenges and complexities of making a new country home, and the richness and value they have brought to New Zealand, whether they arrived a week ago or 100 years ago.&nbsp;
Recently at an event celebrating EID I was able to talk to 3 young 2nd generation Somali Kiwis about Somalia. The beauty of the country, rich in history and with so much potential but facing continued challenges.
They love being Kiwis and love New Zealand but remain so proud of their Somali heritage.&nbsp;
My message is I’m a 4th generation Kiwi of Irish descent and very proud of both being Kiwi and of my Irish heritage. I have the privilege of not just looking through the eyes of our ethnic communities through a New Zealand lens but also in many cases through the country-of-origin lens.&nbsp;
I believe this experience will help me be an informed, effective, passionate Minister and advocate, providing loyal service to our Ethnic Communities.
My priorities
There are four key areas that I will focus on as Minister to ensure that Ethnic Communities thrive in New Zealand: economic growth, security and resilience, emergency management, and social cohesion.
Economic growth
First, economic growth.
Many of you will have seen the Prime Minister’s State of the Nation speech.&nbsp; In that speech, the PM focused almost exclusively on economic growth as the main priority for our Government.
Why?&nbsp;Because economic growth is vital for improving quality of life. For delivering better infrastructure. For providing Kiwis with more choices. And for giving a sense that better days lie ahead.
Ethnic Communities already make a huge contribution to our economy.
In 2021, this contribution was estimated at $64 billion. The average value of export goods for ethnic businesses is more than double the New Zealand average.&nbsp; However, there are barriers that need to be addressed to unlock the full potential of these businesses.
At the Ethnic Xchange business symposium the Ministry facilitated last year, people identified what the Government could do to increase foreign investment.&nbsp; Business owners said long waiting times with the Overseas Investment Office and a lack of coordination between agencies put off foreign investors.
The Government is taking action. We are setting up Invest New Zealand to be a ‘one-stop-shop’ to attract and promote foreign investment.&nbsp;
We are making changes to the Overseas Investment Act to make investment rules less restrictive and more welcoming of investment.
The changes will ensure that for many investments, decisions will be made in just 15 days, where the application isn’t contrary to New Zealand’s national interest.&nbsp;
And we announced changes to the Active Investor Plus Visa to simplify the categories, increase the scope of acceptable investments and remove other potential barriers to investment, such as the English language requirement.
Last month, we held a global infrastructure investment summit to showcase New Zealand’s infrastructure pipeline and growth sectors.
You may be aware that I recently travelled to India with the Prime Minister.
During that trip I saw first-hand the value and strength of the relationship between New Zealand and India, and our trading relationship was very clear.&nbsp; All of this shows the Government’s commitment to growing the economy.
Security and resilience
Second, I want to talk about security and resilience.
Foreign interference affects the safety and security of everyone in New Zealand. &nbsp;The Government is clear that we do not condone foreign interference in New Zealand. It is particularly concerning that some members of our Ethnic Communities are experiencing undue pressure and suppression of rights from foreign states. This is unacceptable.
As Minister, I want to acknowledge that Ethnic Communities’ resilience is a national security asset to all of New Zealand.&nbsp; I’m committed to delivering practical support that will help our communities to withstand foreign interference and to ask for help when they need it.
We’ve released resources in 24 languages to raise awareness about foreign interference in New Zealand. Including case studies, information about your rights, keeping safe online and how to report foreign interference.
This is only the beginning of the work. I know the Ministry for Ethnic Communities is working hard, including looking internationally, to ensure what it produces for our communities is world-class.
While we’ve started to shine a light on foreign interference there is more to be done.&nbsp; Work will continue with a range of communities to develop and release more resources later this year.
Emergency management
Third, I want to talk about emergency management.
We can’t get away from the fact that New Zealand is prone to emergencies. Many of us have experienced the devastating impacts of floods, cyclones and earthquakes, and have learned about them first hand.
Recent events have highlighted gaps in the system, particularly in how emergency responses account for the linguistic, cultural, and religious needs of Ethnic Communities.
The support provided was often not responsive to language, cultural or religious needs. And important information in different languages was slow in getting to the people who needed it.
The Government has committed to making changes to the emergency management system to ensure it is fit for purpose.&nbsp;
The changes will build capability and capacity, support local government and help different parts of the system to work better together.&nbsp; They are based on the idea that everyone needs to be part of preparing and responding to emergencies and recovering afterwards.
Our Ethnic Communities often stand up in times of emergencies to provide life services for the entire community.&nbsp; I have asked NEMA to make sure this important role is formally recognised and codified in the new Emergency Management legislation.&nbsp;
There has been positive progress made in recent years.&nbsp; The Get Ready website, which provides information about what to do before, during and after an emergency, is translated into 14 languages. This proved to be a valuable resource during Cyclone Gabrielle.
NEMA have also told me they are close to completing a resource about what support is available and where to find it.&nbsp;
This resource can be distributed to communities in multiple languages as soon an emergency happens, rather than taking days to develop and translate.
You can have confidence that the needs of Ethnic Communities will be reflected in NEMA’s work.&nbsp;
Social cohesion
Finally, I want to talk about social cohesion.
New Zealand is becoming increasingly diverse.&nbsp; With Ethnic Communities expected to make up one-third of the population in the next two decades, it is essential that we build cohesive and safe communities.
We must build an inclusive society where all communities feel a sense of belonging and where discrimination and prejudice have no place.&nbsp;
I have heard concerns from many of you about experiences of harassment, Islamophobia, and antisemitism. These are issues we must confront directly.
I’m also particularly concerned about the impact geopolitical events overseas are having on domestic social cohesion.
It’s important we don’t let overseas tensions and conflict play out between our communities here.
I am committed to listening, learning and taking action to deliver relevant and tangible initiatives that will make a difference for Ethnic Communities.
Ensuring that we don’t just talk about social cohesion but do things to actively strengthen it.
I want to explore more ways to foster Ethnic Communities’ sense of belonging to and integration with New Zealand society.
I would like better ways to bring faith and community leaders together to build bridges and unite communities.
The Ministry for Ethnic Communities is actively fostering social cohesion through community engagement, interfaith dialogue, and targeted funding. And I am committed to continuing these efforts and identifying further ways to strengthen ties between communities.
Other issues
While some issues fall outside my direct ministerial responsibilities, I remain committed to advocating for the needs of Ethnic Communities.
For example, mental health remains a pressing concern.&nbsp;
Research indicates that Middle Eastern, Latin American, and African youth face disproportionately high rates of mental health struggles, yet cultural barriers often prevent individuals from seeking help.&nbsp;
I will work closely with the Minister for Mental Health to ensure that culturally appropriate support services are accessible to all who need them.
Closing
New Zealand’s Ethnic Communities make an invaluable contribution to our society—socially, culturally, and economically. My commitment as Minister is to ensure that these contributions are recognised, valued, and celebrated.
By working together, we can build a stronger, more inclusive nation—one where diversity is seen as a strength, and where every community has the opportunity to thrive.
Thank you for being here today.&nbsp; I look forward to continuing these important conversations and strengthening our relationships.
Nō reira, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou, tēnā koutou katoa.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 10:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124760</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Security resources to support ethnic communities</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/security-resources-support-ethnic-communities</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Ministry for Ethnic Communities has released resources to support people in New Zealand who may be subject to foreign interference, Ethnic Communities Minister Mark Mitchell says.

“Foreign interference impacts the safety and security of everyone in New Zealand.

“Some of our Ethnic Communities in New Zealand are receiving unwanted attention from foreign states aiming to suppress their protected rights and freedoms, including their right to freedom of expression.

“As a Government we are clear that we do not condone foreign interference in New Zealand.

“In my role as the Minister for Ethnic Communities, I want to acknowledge that our Ethnic Communities’ resilience is a national security asset to all of New Zealand.&nbsp;

“The New Zealand public being alert to the threat of foreign interference is a strength. We want to encourage more open conversations and vigilance.&nbsp;We can all help keep New Zealand safe by telling NZSIS or Police about any concerning behaviour or activity.

“I am committed to delivering practical support that will help our communities to withstand foreign interference and to ask for help when they need.”&nbsp;

The Ministry for Ethnic Communities, as part of an all-of government work programme to tackle foreign interference, has released resources in 24 languages with information about:


Foreign interference in New Zealand
Examples of foreign interference including case studies from the New Zealand Security Intelligence Service
Your rights in New Zealand
How to report foreign interference
Keeping safe online
Keeping your organisation safe online
Information about the draft Crimes (Countering Foreign Interference) Amendment Bill.

“This first release of resources will shine a light on foreign interference. There is more work to be done,” says Mr Mitchell.

The Ministry will continue to work with a range of communities to release additional resources and guidance later in the year.

Community Resources are available on the Ministry for Ethnic Communities website:&nbsp;https://www.ethniccommunities.govt.nz/programmes/security-and-resilience/
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 10:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124759</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Minister to speak at global Space Symposium </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/minister-speak-global-space-symposium</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Space Minister Judith Collins will travel to the United States next week to attend the 40th Space Symposium.
“I’m looking forward to returning to the Space Symposium to continue championing New Zealand as the place to do space-related business,” Ms Collins says.
“The Symposium draws companies and government representatives from around the world, and it’s an excellent opportunity to show that we’re open for business.
“I’ll be promoting New Zealand’s rapidly growing place in the space and advanced aviation sectors.
“Last year we conducted the third highest number of launches in the world. This is an achievement we want to build on as we seek to grow the economy and ease the cost of living for New Zealanders.”
Ms Collins will deliver a speech about New Zealand’s space and advanced aviation sectors, sign a Memorandum of Cooperation between New Zealand and the State of Colorado, host a reception to showcase New Zealand’s space sector, and undertake a range of meetings across her space portfolio. &nbsp;
“I’m looking forward to meeting Colorado Governor Jared Polis again, and following through on an agreement we discussed when we last met. This Memorandum of Cooperation will deepen our relationship and offer opportunities for our aerospace, tech, science and geothermal sectors.”&nbsp;
&nbsp;Ms Collins is away from April 8-12.&nbsp;&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 15:39:32 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124758</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Process to consider establishing a sika deer Herd of Special Interest begins</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/process-consider-establishing-sika-deer-herd-special-interest-begins</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Almost 12 years after the passing of Herds of Special Interest (HOSI) legislation, the formal process that will look into designating New Zealand’s first HOSI has begun, Hunting and Fishing Minister James Meager has announced.
“Hunters are one of the biggest conservation tools we have in New Zealand, and we are committed to community-led management of valued introduced species like deer and tahr in some key places,” says Mr Meager.
“I have recently received a HOSI proposal for the Central North Island sika herd in the Kaimanawa and Kaweka Forest Parks from the Central North Island Sika Foundation, and under the Game Animal Council Act 2013 have decided to begin the process to consider formally designating our country’s first Herd of Special Interest.
“A HOSI provides an opportunity for communities and government to proactively manage highly valued New Zealand game animal herds on conservation land. Not only will a HOSI reduce the environmental impacts of large deer populations, they will improve the condition of herds so hunters have better, larger-bodied, more sustainable populations to hunt.
“The Central North Island Sika Foundation have presented a &nbsp;proposal which is a great starting point, and reflects the ongoing passion they have for improving the management and health of the central North Island sika herd and the environment they live in.
“The proposed sika HOSI would cover over 125,000 hectares of Kaimanawa and Kaweka Forest Parks, and complement efforts by others in the area, like local landowners, to better manage the deer population.”
The goals of the proposed HOSI are to enhance hunter participation in sika deer management, improve hunter satisfaction with sika venison quality and hunting experience, and reduce animal numbers to achieve sustainable forest regeneration. Herds would be managed in a way that improves hunting opportunities and outcomes, while maintaining or improving conservation values.
More information about the sika HOSI proposal is available on the Department of Conservation website here:&nbsp;Herds of Special Interest.
The next phase will involve targeted consultation with stakeholders – including the Ministry for Primary Industries, the Game Animal Council, Department of Conversation, the Conservation Authority, relevant regional councils, conservation boards and iwi.
Public consultation on a draft sika herd management plan will begin after targeted consultation is complete.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 14:29:33 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124757</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Speech to Project Auckland</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/speech/speech-project-auckland</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Check against delivery.Kia ora and thank you so much for inviting me here today. It’s great to be with you all.Can I start by thanking Fran O’Sullivan for her hard work in organising and supporting this annual event and the also NZME for sponsoring the event as always.&nbsp;I’d also like to acknowledge our Deputy Mayor Desley Simpson, Councillor Richard Hills, and my colleague the Honourable Chris Bishop, the Minister of many things relevant to Auckland’s future and success – Transport, Housing, RMA Reform, Infrastructure – the list goes on. He is also, importantly, Leader of the House because you can’t change the law if he doesn’t let you change the law, so it’s very important to have the Leader of the House on site – great to see you here.&nbsp;Also, the opposition spokesperson for Auckland, Carmel Sepuloni, and Shanan Halbert – lovely to see you here today as well.It’s always good to be with you all as leaders of our city – people who believe in Auckland’s future and are committed to its success.This shared commitment mirrors our Government’s focus on Going for Growth – driving positive change for this city, and delivering real results.&nbsp;
Context&nbsp;
As a Government, we have set a clear, decisive plan to get New Zealand back on track.There is no doubt that our country – and this city – faces significant challenges.At the heart of those challenges are the economy, inflation, and interest rates, which have been tightening household budgets and stifled economic growth.&nbsp;The Government has spent the last 18 months focused on the basics – rebuilding our economy, restoring law and order, and delivering better public services, particularly in health and education.By reducing wasteful spending, reining in inflation, and lowering interest rates, we are easing the pressure on families and mortgages and giving businesses the certainty they need to grow and invest.We campaigned on this, and we are starting to see the green shoots of economic recovery.Inflation is back within the one to three per cent band, and interest rates are falling. This is good news for Kiwi households and businesses and is critical to easing the cost-of-living pressures for New Zealanders.&nbsp;&nbsp;Just last week, it was confirmed that our economy has also started to turn the corner, with GDP growing by 0.7 percent in the three months to December – ahead of what the economists were projecting – welcome news after a long period of economic decline, which we inherited, leaving Kiwis feeling poorer.&nbsp;Under Christopher Luxon’s leadership, our Government is Going for Growth, and working tirelessly to sustain this momentum, because a stronger economy means more jobs, better incomes, and more opportunities for Kiwis to get ahead.&nbsp;Rebuilding our economy also requires discipline across every part of government, local and central – delivering the services and infrastructure that Kiwis need, while ensuring every dollar is spent wisely to produce tangible results.&nbsp;This disciplined approach is especially crucial for Auckland – home to 34 per cent of our population and generating 38 per cent of New Zealand’s GDP.Rebuilding our economy means the Government can continue to invest in the priorities facing our city, whether that is better schools, more doctors and nurses in our hospitals, or the infrastructure needed for our fast-growing city.As Minister for Auckland, my role is to champion this city’s interests and ensure it receives the attention and investment it rightfully deserves from central Government, and I am proud of what we have already achieved as a Government.&nbsp;
&nbsp;
Delivering for Auckland
Since entering government, we have moved quickly deliver on our promises and get Auckland back on track.&nbsp;We axed the Auckland Regional Fuel Tax, removing 11.5 cents per litre from the cost of fuel.We delivered tax relief for hardworking Aucklanders, with average-income households receiving up to $102 a fortnight.We have also prevented a 25.8 per cent increase in water rates through our Local Water Done Well plan, ensuring Aucklanders have access to affordable and sustainable water services.This will save Aucklanders around $899 million in water and wastewater charges over four years through the Watercare Charter.&nbsp;I want to acknowledge the team from Watercare for the excellent work they’ve done, as well as Auckland Council who have partnered with the Government to enable this deal.&nbsp;The deal with Auckland Council to financially separate Watercare has also built huge confidence in the pipeline of water infrastructure in Auckland.&nbsp;A major sign of this confidence was the decision by tunnelling company, Ghella, who are building the Auckland Central Interceptor, to keep their tunnel boring machine in Auckland, following the completion of the central interceptor tunnels this Friday. They see the growing pipeline of water infrastructure projects that require delivering in our city.&nbsp;This is what real confidence in the infrastructure pipeline looks like and it’s a privilege to play a part in delivering that.&nbsp;We have also opened new state-of-the-art radiology equipment at Auckland City Hospital’s Regional Cancer and Blood Service.We’ve deployed additional cops on the beat – raising beat cops to 51 in the CBD – strengthening law and order to improve safety in the inner city and across Auckland.We scrapped Auckland Light Rail, halting a project that haemorrhaged over $228 million without delivering a single metre of track.We have introduced legislation for Time of Use Schemes, which will support the Government’s and Auckland Council’s efforts to reduce congestion across the city and improve efficiency of our roading network.&nbsp;We set a clear direction for both roading and public transport projects across Auckland, including the Northland Corridor, Mill Road Stage 1, the North-West Alternative State Highway, the Northwestern Busway and the Airport to Botany Busway so Aucklanders can have a clear plan of future transport projects for the city – both roading and public transport connections that this city needs for the future.&nbsp;And we are restoring democratic accountability for transport decisions, ensuring Auckland ratepayers have a genuine say in shaping our city.Our track record as a Government demonstrates our commitment to delivering real outcomes for Auckland and getting our city back on track.
&nbsp;
What’s next for Auckland
&nbsp;
But the question is what’s next for Auckland?While we’ve achieved a lot in a short space of time, our work isn’t done. There is much more to do. Two key areas of work that will be underway over the next 12-18 months, which I think are critically to our city’s success, is capitalising on the benefits of the City Rail Link and developing an Auckland Regional Deal.The next 12-18 months see significant change in Auckland as we look forward to the completion of the City Rail Link.&nbsp;This project, started under the last National Government, will be truly transformational for the city and unlock huge benefits for Aucklanders, including reduced travel times and increased opportunities for development along our rail corridor.&nbsp;Once complete, the City Rail Link will be truly city shaping, and will have a significant impact beyond just making transport more accessible for Aucklanders.&nbsp;Unlocking the benefits of the CRL is key to Auckland’s success. Both the Government and Auckland Council have invested billions of dollars into this project and we must make sure that we are getting the benefits from it.&nbsp;Whether it is the work Transport Minister Chris Bishop is delivering with Auckland Council to remove level crossings to keep traffic moving safely in our suburbs, or it is unlocking development around train stations across Auckland, we must make sure that the city maximises the benefits.&nbsp;The Government has also recently welcomed proposals around regional deals, and I welcome Auckland Council’s proposal which has been put forward as part of that process.&nbsp;I hope that maximising the City Rail Link benefits can be part of that deal because that is something we must jointly ensure happens for the city.&nbsp;Regional deals are an opportunity to bring Councils, Government, Business, Iwi and community together with a longer-term view than just the three-year political cycle, about what’s need to enable the key issues to be unlock, whether that economic growth, productivity, housing, or infrastructure.&nbsp;I’m looking forward to the opportunity we have before us to build on the work already underway with Auckland Council, and how a regional deal could support that.&nbsp;As Minister of Auckland, I will be advocating for Auckland to be the first cab off the rank for a regional deal so we can build on the strong progress we have already made for Auckland in the past 18 months.&nbsp;A regional deal will be a long-term plan for the city, outlining how both local and central government can work together to unlock economic growth in our city, build houses, and deliver the infrastructure needed for this city.&nbsp;It is also an opportunity to outline how central and local governments need to work together to solve problems and deliver tangible solutions.&nbsp;Taxpayers and Ratepayers are ultimately the same people – and they expect central and local governments to work together to deliver on their priorities over the long term.&nbsp;Regional deals are an opportunity to do just that and I will be working closely with Auckland Council on their plan to deliver a Regional Deal for Auckland.&nbsp;But, great infrastructure and economic reforms also need high-quality public services, particularly in health, that are efficient and put patients first.
&nbsp;
Keeping Auckland healthy
&nbsp;
That’s why we’re determined to ensure Aucklanders have timely, quality access to healthcare.A lot has changed since I last spoke to you in March, when I was talking about potholes – but even Bernard Orsman managed to find a pothole at Greenlane Hospital carpark yesterday, and we got it fixed.&nbsp;Some might say I traded one challenge for an even bigger one. In a growing city like Auckland, we need a resilient health system, so that rising demand from a growing population doesn’t mean waitlists balloon out even more than they already have.The Government is putting more money into health than ever before and we are focussing our health system on delivering the timely and quality healthcare for all New Zealanders.&nbsp;To achieve this – we have restored national health targets – which are key to delivering timely and quality healthcare.&nbsp;Unfortunately over the last 6 years, we’ve seen the results go backwards for patients, whether its Kiwis waiting longer in emergency departments or elective surgeries, which increased from 1000 people more than four months in 2017 to over 27,000 waiting more than four months in 2023.It is unacceptable and New Zealanders deserve better. Health targets have been restored to deliver better outcomes for patients because what gets measured gets managed.But performance also depends on infrastructure. Auckland’s population is growing, so we need modern hospitals to keep up.For the expectant new mother needing maternity care.For the elderly patient needing a hip replacement.For the injured tradie needing urgent care after an accident on the job.
&nbsp;
Health Infrastructure Plan
&nbsp;
At the recent New Zealand Infrastructure Summit, I highlighted 67 health infrastructure projects – valued at $6.39 billion – which are in the pipeline across the country.&nbsp;$1.5 billion of that is in Auckland, including Manukau Health Park here in Auckland, large scale remediation programmes across our estate at Auckland Hospital and Greenlane Hospital.But at current estimates, we cannot build capacity fast enough to meet the demands of a growing population.&nbsp;Today, I am providing an update on the Health Infrastructure Plan that Cabinet is developing. This plan will set a direction for the next 10 to 20 years to ensure that as a country, we build the right things in the right places at the right size and scale.While each project will require its own business case, the plan will set a long-term view of health infrastructure needs across the country and gives Health New Zealand a clear plan to work upon.&nbsp;We know that hospitals across the Auckland region are experiencing pronounced bed shortages, which are expected to increase as the population grows.South Auckland in particular is one of our fastest-growing communities, with significant health challenges.&nbsp;This community experiences higher rates of infectious conditions and long term conditions such as diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and chronic respiratory disease.&nbsp;The health needs of South Auckland are compounding, and this impacts the whole region, with both Middlemore and Auckland City Hospital under pressure to service the south Auckland population – and this pressure will only continue to grow.A new site in South Auckland has long been acknowledged by the region’s health planning as necessary to meet the growing demand.&nbsp;Today, I’m confirming that as part of the Health Infrastructure Plan, a new major hospital in South Auckland is being explored.&nbsp;The next steps involve detailed planning by Health New Zealand and securing land to accelerate development.This hospital would work alongside Middlemore, adding more beds, modern surgical theatres, and expanded emergency services – easing pressure on the system and improving outcomes for Aucklanders.&nbsp;Kiwis deserve better than long waits in overcrowded emergency departments and long waits for surgery. Patients come first, and investing in infrastructure is key to delivering that.The Health Infrastructure Plan has been considered by Cabinet and will be published in the coming weeks&nbsp;
&nbsp;
Conclusion
&nbsp;
We have a clear growth agenda for Auckland. We’ve taken decisive action to ease the cost of living, restore law and order, and keep our city moving.Auckland must be a city that works for its people – where businesses thrive, families can afford to live, people can travel quickly and safely, and everyone has access to timely, quality healthcare.That’s my focus.Thanks very much for having me here.Thank you, and I look forward to continuing this work alongside you all.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 18:00:00 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124756</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Disability working groups announced</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/disability-working-groups-announced</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Strong interest in the development of a refreshed New Zealand disability strategy has been welcomed by Disability Issues Minister Louise Upston.
Membership of the strategy working groups was announced today, drawn from the disabled community, industry and government agencies. The groups will develop actions in the five key areas of education, employment, health, housing and justice.&nbsp;
“There has been a particularly strong response from the disability community, reflecting the commitment of people who want to be part of this important work,” Louise Upston says.
“The Ministry of Disabled People - Whaikaha received almost 350 expressions of interest from the disability community before making their appointment decisions.
“In total, Whaikaha is announcing 26 members of the groups, including the chairs, who I congratulate today:

Education – Grant Cleland 
Employment – Lorraine Toki 
Health – Dr Josephine Herman 
Housing - Daniel Clay 
Justice&nbsp;– Paul Gibson&nbsp;

“The Ministry is taking a new approach to developing the new strategy, and I will be excited to see the results.&nbsp;
“Ultimately, the purpose is to improve the lives of disabled people. For instance, recent data from the Stats NZ Household Disability Survey found disabled New Zealanders continue to face many barriers, for example in education, employment and housing.
“We know 1 in 6 New Zealanders are disabled, yet three quarters of unemployed disabled people want to be working which means creating employment opportunities must be an important focus.&nbsp;
“Disabled people, like non-disabled people, want to participate in their communities, to thrive and make decisions about their own lives.
“The strategy refresh represents huge opportunities to make a positive difference,” Louise Upston says.
The Ministry of Disabled People – Whaikaha is managing the refresh process. The draft strategy will go to the wider disabled community later this year for further review before being agreed by Cabinet.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 11:40:17 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124755</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Melling transport improvements to start this year</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/melling-transport-improvements-start-year</link>
  <description><![CDATA[
The Melling Road of Regional Significance project will start this year.
The project includes a new grade-separated interchange and bridge, improvements to walking and cycling infrastructure, and better access to public transport like buses and trains through relocation of the train station.
The wider programme also includes a new cycling and pedestrian City Link Bridge connecting the relocated train station to the Hutt CBD.

Construction on the Melling Transport Improvements project on SH2 in the Hutt Valley will start this year, Minister of Transport Chris Bishop says.
The NZ Transport Agency (NZTA) has now signed the delivery contract with AECOM and Fletcher Construction to deliver the project.
“This is a critical project for the future of the Hutt Valley and will be transformational for the city of Lower Hutt – reducing congestion, improving safety, boosting public transport and active transport, and driving economic growth.
“Of course, Melling is just one part of a complex jigsaw puzzle of the RiverLink programme being delivered by NZTA, Greater Wellington Regional Council and Hutt City Council. This wider programme will significantly increase the Hutt Valley’s resilience and improve protection from floods and severe weather events.
“Around 40,000 vehicles travel north and south of Melling on the state highway every day, making it one of the busiest intersections in Lower Hutt and the wider network. It’s a severe bottleneck for traffic that slows down commuters and freight.
“The project includes the construction of a new grade-separated Melling interchange and bridge over the Hutt River, improvements to walking and cycling infrastructure, and better access to public transport like buses and trains through the relocation of the train station with park and ride facilities south of the current station.
“The wider Riverlink programme, which also includes flood protection and city revitalisation, has an overall budget of approximately $1.5 billion comprising approximately $1 billion from NZTA (construction costs, property, consenting, design, investigations, demolition and other NZTA managed costs), $295 million from the Greater Wellington Regional Council and $180 million from the Hutt City Council.”
“The project has been undoubtedly challenging from a cost perspective. NZTA has worked hard with AECOM and Fletcher Construction to bring costs for the project down and deliver value for money in a challenging environment. Approximately $200 million in savings has been found, and Cabinet agreed in late 2024 to provide NZTA with additional Crown funding to deliver this vital Road of Regional Significance.
“I can also confirm that the wider programme will include the construction of a City Link Bridge, a key connection point between the Lower Hutt city centre and the relocated train station, providing better access to public transport like buses and trains.
“The bridge will be delivered by Hutt City Council and will help unlock better public transport opportunities and housing within the city. The government has agreed to a variation of Infrastructure Acceleration Funding (IAF) already provided to Hutt City Council to enable this to proceed.
“The Melling Transport Improvements project will contribute to an already strong pipeline of work underway or about to get underway, while also supporting local businesses, trades, and wider infrastructure opportunities in the region.
“Over the coming months, NZTA will continue working through several elements of the project’s early stages, including finalising the detailed design. This will help ensure that when construction starts later this year, NZTA can work as efficiently as possible and keep the project on track.
“I am confident the transport improvements at Melling will have significant benefits for motorists, freight, and those travelling to, through and from Lower Hutt once work is complete, and I want to thank Mayor Campbell Barry, GWRC Chair Daran Ponter, NZTA and Ngāti Toa and Taranaki Whānui.
“Today is a great day for the Hutt Valley. Getting on with the Melling project will give much needed certainty to residents, businesses, and the wider community that have been calling for these improvements for many years. I look forward to being on site later this year to turn the first sod and kick off construction.”
The Melling interchange and bridge construction is expected to be completed in 2031 with demolition of the old bridge to follow in 2032.
Notes to editor:

The SH2 Melling Transport Improvements project is one of three projects within the RiverLink project.
RiverLink is a partnership between NZTA, Hutt City Council (HCC), Greater Wellington Regional Council (GWRC), and mana whenua Ngāti Toa Rangatira and Taranaki Whānui ki te Upoko o te Ika.
The wider RiverLink programme includes crucial flood protection and river restoration work flood protection and city centre infrastructure upgrades.

More information about the SH2 Melling Transport Improvements can be found at www.nzta.govt.nz/melling and wider programme works at www.teawakairangi.co.nz
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 10:01:40 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124754</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Two new charter schools announced </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/two-new-charter-schools-announced</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Two new sponsors have been contracted to open two new charter schools and will join the seven that are successfully operating already, Associate Education Minister David Seymour announced today.&nbsp;
“Tōtara Park School and Twin Oaks Classical School, both in Auckland, have signed contracts with the Charter School Agency,” Mr Seymour says.
“Twin Oaks will cater for students in Years 1 to 9 when it opens in July this year and by 2027 will accommodate students up to Year 13.&nbsp;
“Tōtara Park will open in Term 1 next year. It will begin with a Years 1 to 4 cohort and by 2027 it will take students up to Year 6.&nbsp;
“Both these schools demonstrate the innovation inherent in the charter school model.&nbsp;
“Students attending Twin Oaks Classical School will spend the first three days of the week at school and the last two days learning from home. The school will train and support parents and provide clear expectations for work that students complete at home. This partnership approach is based on the classical Charlotte Mason approach.&nbsp;
“Tōtara Park is based on the Pared model of schooling which features a personalised mentoring system. Mentors support parents in exercising their duty as primary educators. An individual mentor, selected from the teachers and learning assistants at the school, is appointed to each student and given the necessary training to fulfil this role.&nbsp;
“Expressions of interest for new charter schools have closed. As expected, there has been keen interest from sponsors. The next step for sponsors who have expressed interest is the application form which must be completed by May 16. EOIs for state or state-integrated schools considering converting to charter schools close at 5pm on 11 April, and applications for converting schools close at noon on 27 June.
“This demand not only highlights the need, but also the commitment of sponsors to provide innovative educational opportunities.&nbsp;
“Charter schools provide educators with greater autonomy and create diversity in New Zealand’s education system. They have been proven to raise overall educational achievement, especially for students who are underachieving or disengaged from the standard system.&nbsp;
“Charter schools have greater flexibility to respond to diverse student needs in innovative ways, but in return they have greater accountability.&nbsp;&nbsp;
“We’re on our way to building a lasting network of schools that will support and improve the educational achievement.”&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Mon, 31 Mar 2025 14:12:23 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124753</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Pharmac Listens To Patient Voice</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/pharmac-listens-patient-voice</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Associate Health Minister David Seymour welcomes Pharmac opening consultation on their proposal to fund two brands of oestradiol patches.&nbsp;
“Increasing availability of medicines has always been a priority of mine. For many New Zealanders, funding for pharmaceuticals is life or death, or the difference between a life of pain and suffering or living freely,” Mr Seymour says.
“For the first time, Pharmac has its own Minister. Last year I outlined in my letter of expectations that Pharmac should have appropriate processes for ensuring that people living with an illness, along with their carers and family, can participate in and provide input into decision-making processes around medicines – this is committed to in the Act-National Coalition Agreement.
“Pharmac received significant feedback at the end of last year about a decision to move to Estradiol TDP Mylan as the only funded brand of oestradiol patch. They heard very clearly that the TDP Mylan brand of patch did not work for everyone, and that people wanted options.&nbsp;
From today Pharmac will begin consulting on a proposal to fund two brands of oestradiol patches, Estradot and Estradiol TDP Mylan, from December 2025.
“Pharmac has been working and engaging with people who use oestradiol patches, menopause specialists, doctors, nurses, pharmacists, advocacy groups and petition founders to reflect their feedback in a new proposal to fund both Estradot and TDP Mylan patches,” Mr Seymour says.
“The redirection of Pharmac remains positive and continues towards a&nbsp;more adaptable and patient-centered approach to funding medicines.
“The decision to begin consultation to fund Estradot and Estradiol TDP Mylan from December 2025 follows the Pharmac Consumer Engagement Workshop Report, last year’s Medicines Summit, my letter of expectations, and the acceptance of Patient Voice Aotearoa’s White Paper as steps towards a system which works for the people it serves.
“The Government is doing its part. Last year this government allocated Pharmac its largest ever budget of $6.294 billion over four years, and a $604 million uplift to give Pharmac the financial support it needs to carry out its functions - negotiating the best deals for medicine for New Zealanders.
“We want to build a world-class health system, and that requires access to world-class medicines.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Mar 2025 13:05:59 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124752</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Appointments to Pharmac Board</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/appointments-pharmac-board</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Associate Health Minister with responsibility for Pharmac David Seymour has appointed two new people to the Pharmac Board and reappointed a current member for a second term.&nbsp;
Chartered accountant Talia Anderson-Town joined the Board in 2021 and has now been appointed for a further three years.&nbsp;
The two new Board members are:

Lucy Elwood, a lawyer with significant governance and leadership experience including roles as CEO of the Cancer Society of New Zealand and Chair of Rare Disorders NZ
Anna Adams, a barrister with experience in health law, public policy and regulatory systems. Her previous governance roles have included Board membership of the Civil Aviation Authority of New Zealand.&nbsp;

Other Board members include Chair Paula Bennett, Peter Bramley, and Dr Margaret Wilsher.&nbsp;
“Last year in my letter of expectations I made it clear that I want Pharmac to work in partnership with consumers, clinicians, suppliers and the health sector to improve health outcomes for New Zealanders underpinned by robust data and evidence,” says Mr Seymour.
“I’m confident this board will provide the strategic direction and governance needed to deliver on my expectations for a world class medicines and medical devices agency.”
He also thanked departing Board member Diana Siew, who steps down this month after a three-year term.&nbsp;
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 16:47:42 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124751</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Mental Health targets show increasing access </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/mental-health-targets-show-increasing-access</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Minister for Mental Health Matt Doocey says second quarter mental health and addiction target data indicates New Zealanders are seeing genuine progress in improving wait times and increasing access to timely mental health support.
“It is encouraging to see all three of our wait time targets are improving and two of those targets are already being met at a national level,” Mr Doocey says.
“This includes a 3.1 per cent increase in the overall number of people who are now accessing primary mental health and addiction services within one week. And a 1.5 per cent increase of Kiwis accessing specialist mental health and addiction services within three weeks.
“The results released today reinforce the Government’s commitment to increasing access to timely mental health and addiction support. I’m pleased the targets and numbers are going in the right direction overall which results in better access for Kiwis.
“There is still plenty of work to be done, and I will continue in my efforts to drive change. This is evident at a local level where certain districts and population groups aren’t receiving the same level of access.
“While it’s positive to see an increase in the shorter stays in ED target, today’s results highlight there is a lot more work to do to reach 95 per cent of people admitted, discharged, or transferred from an ED within six hours.
“This data provides a clearer understanding than we’ve ever had before. It provides clarity on the regions that are underperforming and in need of further improvement to bring them up to the national target.
“I’ve recently met with Health NZ’s four regional deputy chief executives and tasked them with developing action plans for supporting and improving underperforming services within the regions.
“As New Zealand’s first Minister for Mental Health, I am clear that accountability is vital and that we will continue to take a proactive approach to improving access and providing timely mental health and addiction support when and where it’s needed.”
Note for editors:

Factsheets for quarter two results can be found here.
Faster access to specialist mental health and addiction services: target of 80 percent of people accessing specialist mental health and addiction services are seen within three weeks.

81.9 percent of people were seen by specialist mental health service within three weeks in quarter 2, compared with 80.4 percent in quarter 1.


Faster access to primary mental health and addiction services: target of 80 percent of people accessing primary mental health and addiction services through the Access and Choice programme are seen within one week.

83.9 percent of people were seen by primary mental health service within one week in quarter 2, compared with 80.8 percent in quarter 1.


Shorter mental health and addiction-related stays in emergency departments: target of 95 percent of mental health and addiction-related emergency department presentations are admitted, discharged, or transferred from an emergency department within six hours.o&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;65 percent of people were admitted, discharged, or transferred from an emergency department within six hours in quarter 2, compared with 63.5 percent in quarter 1.
Increased mental health and addiction workforce development: target of training 500 mental health and addiction professionals each year.

Increased mental health and addiction workforce development - 457


Strengthened focus on prevention and early intervention: target of 25 percent of mental health and addiction investment is allocated towards prevention and early intervention.

24.4% of investment allocated towards prevention and early intervention



]]></description>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 09:00:16 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124750</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Repeal of 7AA puts child wellbeing first</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/repeal-7aa-puts-child-wellbeing-first</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Children’s Minister Karen Chhour has welcomed the passing of legislation to repeal section 7AA of the Oranga Tamariki Act by Parliament.
The Bill’s passing will enable Oranga Tamariki—Ministry for Children and its frontline staff to focus first and foremost on the safety and wellbeing of children when creating care arrangements, says Minister for Children, Karen Chhour.
“This Bill will allow Oranga Tamariki to focus on its primary duty first, which is the care and protection of young people, making sure they are safe from harm.
While Section 7AA was well-intended, it also resulted in children being put second.&nbsp; As the responsible Minister I could not accept or excuse this fact.
We can no longer deny that section 7AA has led to confusion and conflict in a system that cannot afford to get such crucial care decisions wrong.
What happens now, what happens in practice to these young people, matters.
These children’s lives are not lived in theories or in the comfort of academia or privilege. The harm that comes their way is not academic, it is real,” says Ms Chhour.
Frontline staff and many select committee submitters have shared that section 7AA has led to decisions that were not in the best interests of the child in cases where the race of a child was prioritised over their safety and well-being.
“This created a conflict for Oranga Tamariki when making decisions in the best interests of the child or young person.
“This Bill does not stop the consideration of cultural wellbeing of children and young people in the care of Oranga Tamariki, nor will it result in the end of strategic partnerships between iwi and Māori organisations and Oranga Tamariki.
“I want to make clear that this Bill does not negate the importance of cultural connections for children and young people. What the Bill does is creates clarity in decision-making so that safety is indeed the paramount consideration for each and all children and young people.
I have no issue with looking to whānau, hapū, or iwi as a solution for placements, when appropriate, but safety must come first every single time and sadly that has not always been the case,” says Ms Chhour.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 16:45:29 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124749</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>First step towards honouring more veterans on Anzac Day</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/first-step-towards-honouring-more-veterans-anzac-day</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Legislation to formally recognise the service of more New Zealanders as part of official Anzac Day commemorations has passed its first reading in Parliament today, Veterans Minister Chris Penk and Arts, Culture and Heritage Minister Paul Goldsmith say.
“Anzac Day is a significant anniversary for New Zealanders, where we reflect on the costs of service and sacrifice. It is our opportunity to honour those who have served, some of whom gave their lives for our country,” Mr Penk says.
“The Anzac Day Act enshrines in law that we will remember them. Yet, because it does not acknowledge conflicts after 1966, many New Zealanders who have served with great courage in the following decades remain unrecognised under current legislation.
“While April 25 marks the day our soldiers set foot on the Gallipoli Peninsula in 1915, Anzac Day has long become an anniversary of remembrance for those who served beyond the First and Second World Wars. It’s past time that this is reflected in the law.
“Once the Bill passes, Anzac Day will officially commemorate all those who have served New Zealand in wars and war-like situations. This will include those who have given non-military service, such as the Home Guard and members of the Merchant Navy.
“In addition, the Bill will be amended to encompass other troops who took part in the landing at Gallipoli, including those from India and France. At present the Anzac Day Act only recognises troops from the United Kingdom, Australia and New Zealand.”
“New Zealanders deeply appreciate the courage, commitment, and sacrifice of servicemen and women - past and present. Anzac Day stands as a powerful tribute to their service,” Mr Goldsmith says.
“Today's service personnel carry forward a long and proud tradition. It’s time for overdue change - every New Zealander who has served in war and war-like conflicts deserves official recognition and honour. Anzac Day is the right moment to acknowledge them.”
The Anzac Day Amendment Bill is expected to be passed in time for Anzac Day 2026.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 16:04:49 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124747</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Health targets focusing system on delivering more for patients</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/health-targets-focusing-system-delivering-more-patients</link>
  <description><![CDATA[New data highlights that while the Government’s commitment to health targets continues to stabilise the health system, increased service delivery is required to get on top of waitlists, Health Minister Simeon Brown says.
“Ensuring all Kiwis have access to timely, quality healthcare is a priority for the Government. I am encouraged by Health New Zealand’s release of second quarter 2024/25 results today, which show improvements in three of the five health targets,” Mr Brown says.
“Wait times in emergency departments continue to reduce, with 72.1 per cent of patients being admitted or discharged within six hours, an improvement from 67.5 per cent in the previous quarter.
“Access to faster cancer care continues to improve, with 85.9 per cent of patients receiving treatment within 31 days – just 0.1 per cent away from the yearly milestone.
“And more children are now fully immunised, with 77 per cent of two-year-olds being immunised in the second quarter of this year, up from 75.7 per cent in the previous quarter.”
The data also confirms that more work is needed to get on top of waitlists for those waiting over four months for elective treatment and first specialist assessments, which grew by 2,500 per cent and 6,400 per cent respectively under the previous government.
“While performance declined for the elective treatment and first specialist assessment targets, more was delivered by Health New Zealand in 2024, with more Kiwis having their elective surgeries and first specialist assessments than previous years.




&nbsp;
2021
2022
2023
2024




Total first specialist assessments delivered*
608,384
567,901
608,027
624,202


Total elective care delivered
320,328
305,310
338,692
341,276




“However, more people are being added to waitlists than who are receiving treatment or assessments, which means there is still significant work required to improve the pace at which elective treatment and first specialist assessments are being delivered.
“Delivering more at a faster rate than patients are added to waitlists is key to reducing waitlists and wait times.
“That’s why I recently announced the elective boost, partnering with private hospitals to maximise operating capacity and expand procedures. This initiative will deliver 10,579 additional procedures by mid-year, with 2,000 already completed, including cataracts, hip, and knee replacements.
“We are reducing specialist assessment delays by improving waitlist management, expanding service models, and implementing initiatives like AI diabetes retinal screening and Kaitaia’s complete cataract care pathway to free up waitlists.
“To further ease pressure on hospitals and emergency departments, our Government is taking action to ensure New Zealanders have increased access to more doctors and nurses and expanding primary healthcare options.
“The Government is investing more than ever into our health system – a record $30 billion each year – and we expect it to deliver more for patients as a result.
“By measuring what matters and holding the system accountable, we are putting patients first and supporting our frontline healthcare workers to deliver the healthcare New Zealanders need in a timely and quality manner,” Mr Brown says.
* First specialist assessment data for 2024 excludes the Auckland district.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 13:10:24 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124744</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Regional tourism to benefit from $2.45 million boost </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/regional-tourism-benefit-245-million-boost</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Tourism and Hospitality Minister Louise Upston says opening a second multi-million dollar funding round for regional tourism will drive economic growth.

“We know a successful tourism and hospitality sector is crucial for growing our economy,” Louise Upston says.&nbsp;

“Tourism is a crucial part of this Government’s focus on economic growth, with domestic and international tourism expenditure at almost $38 billion and supporting nearly 200,000 jobs

“We also know we need to see visitors in regions outside our main cities, and outside peak periods. Hosting exciting local events is one of the best ways we can do this.

“Today I’m pleased to be announcing that regional tourism organisations will have a pool of $2.45 million to pitch to from the Regional Events Promotion Fund.&nbsp;

“Regions with big ideas can reach out straight away. As Minister, I’m always looking forward to working closely with the sector to help maximise the benefits of tourism and hospitality and support the workforce to grow.

“All ideas are up for discussion, as we reinforce the message that New Zealand is open for business and ready to welcome visitors from home and overseas.

“In this second round, I’m particularly keen to encourage regions which might not traditionally have seen a high volume of domestic tourists to host events which will drive spending and activity in their communities.

“This is the latest in our push to support the tourism sector, including:


$500,000 for marketing New Zealand as the ‘go now’ destination for Australians
$30 million to support conservation visitor related experiences
$9 million for Great Rides cycle infrastructure
$3 million from the International Visitor Conservation and Tourism Levy to secure more business events for New Zealand


“2025 is our chance to reinforce the value of tourism and show what our humming, vibrant country has on show. New Zealand tourism is open for business,” Louise Upston said during comments to&nbsp;the University of Otago Tourism Policy School in Queenstown.

The first round of funding for the Regional Events Promotion Fund saw 132 events approved, with $2.375 million allocated.&nbsp;

Applications for the second round of funding are open now with decisions expected to be made in May 2025.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 13:05:29 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124743</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Statement by Minister Todd McClay following U.S. tariff announcement</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/statement-minister-todd-mcclay-following%C2%A0us-tariff-announcement</link>
  <description><![CDATA[“Today the&nbsp;U.S. has announced a 10 per cent tariff on all imports of good, with many countries facing much higher tariffs on a reciprocal basis. New Zealand exporters will face a&nbsp;10 per cent tariff rate from this weekend. While this is a significant development, New Zealand remains competitive against other exporters in the U.S. market.

New Zealand’s interests are best served in a world where trade flows freely. Tariffs have consequences for the global economy – impacting inflation, demand, currency stability, and economic growth.
While these tariffs create additional costs that will largely be passed on to consumers, New Zealand is in a stronger position than many other countries, some who are facing higher tariff barriers. This reinforces the importance of our work to create new trade opportunities and reduce barriers for our exporters in the EU, UK, UAE, GCC and most recently India.&nbsp;
New Zealand’s bilateral relationship with the U.S. remains strong. We will be talking with the Administration to get more information, and our exporters to better understand the impact this announcement will have.
We will continue to advocate for a rules-based trading system.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 12:20:07 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124742</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Rule of Two for faster access to medicines</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/rule-two-faster-access-medicines</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Associate Health Minister David Seymour is welcoming Cabinet’s decision to enable medicines to be approved in less than 30 days if the product has approval from two recognised overseas jurisdictions.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;
This change is included in the Medicines Amendment Bill (the Bill), which amends the Medicines Act 1981. The pathway will be in operation by early 2026.
The policy will start with Australia, the United States, Canada, the United Kingdom, the European Union, Singapore and Switzerland, as recognised countries. These are the main countries Medsafe currently recognises.&nbsp;
“Faster access to medicines has always been a priority of mine. For many New Zealanders, pharmaceuticals are life or death, or the difference between a life of pain and suffering or living freely,” Mr Seymour says.&nbsp;
“This change will increase access to medicines for Kiwis by introducing a streamlined verification pathway for medicines. People will access new treatments more quickly. This is committed to in the ACT-National and National-NZ First coalition agreements.&nbsp;
“Cabinet has agreed to give the responsible Minister powers to regulate the Rule of Two. That means I will be outlining the proposed regulatory pathway for industry and the public to feedback on via the Select Committee process. This system should be as straightforward as possible to allow New Zealanders the greatest level of access to innovative medicine possible.&nbsp;
“New cars are acceptable for the New Zealand market if they meet at least one of several foreign standards. We can apply the same principle to medicines, if other jurisdictions have already done the work and can ensure the products’ safety, we don’t need to delay patient’s access by doing the exact same tests,” Mr Seymour says.&nbsp;
“This is a common-sense efficiency that costs nothing. It helps Kiwis in need. It can shave months off the approval process. A perfect example of this was with a treatment for asthma which could have been approved by the end of 2022 under this pathway, but was not approved until 16 months later in May 2024.&nbsp;
“This Government is making medicines access a priority because it leads to better patient outcomes. So far, we have:

Changed Pharmac’s process so it can assess a funding application at the same time as Medsafe is assessing the application for regulatory approval
Allocated Pharmac its largest ever budget of $6.294 billion over four years, and a $604 million uplift to give Pharmac the financial support it needs to carry out its functions - negotiating the best deals for medicine for New Zealanders 
Made patient voice a crucial consideration in Pharmac’s funding decisions
Put pseudoephedrine back on the shelves of pharmacies

“We’re committed to ensuring that the regulatory system for pharmaceuticals is not unreasonably holding back access. It will lead to more Kiwis being able to access the medicines they need to live a fulfilling life.”
Notes to editors:&nbsp;
Draft criteria for regulatory pathway rules will likely relate to ensuring that:

manufacturing sites associated with product have evidence of Good Manufacturing Practice (GMP) compliance which is valid to Medsafe’s satisfaction,
if a product is a generic or biosimilar prescription medicine, the innovator or reference product is identical to that approved for New Zealand.

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 10:17:26 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124741</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Strengthening reo Māori accessibility</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/strengthening-reo-m%C4%81ori-accessibility</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Toi te kupu, toi te mana, toi tū te reo.
Talented appointees to prominent reo Māori entities will help grow accessibility to the language and culture in homes and communities, Minister for Māori Development Tama Potaka says.
“Beloved shows from the past like Hōmai Te Pakipaki, popular celebrations like Te Wiki o te Reo Māori and inspiring national events like Te Matatini o Te Kāhui Maunga attract large diverse audiences to reo Māori me ngā tikanga. Stories about Māori told in a uniquely Māori will continue to support language learners and fluent speakers alike as we move to an increasingly digital mediascape.
“The appointments I’m announcing today include leaders in governance, business, broadcasting, and language revitalisation.” The entities and appointments are:
Te Mātāwai

Penetaui Kleskovic is General Manager of Te Aupōuri and Councillor of Ngā Tai o Tokerau Māori Ward. In addition to his te reo expertise, his three-year appointment will bring valuable insights to the board in asset growth and community engagement.

Te Mangai Pāho

Erana Reedy will be appointed for three years. She has 40 years of experience in broadcasting, producing te reo Māori content across radio, television, and online platforms as well as being Chief Operating Officer of Radio Ngāti Porou and Deputy Chair of Te Whakaruruhau o Ngā Reo Irirangi Māori.
Tamalene Painting will be reappointed for three years. She has strong te reo Māori capability, financial skills, and extensive experience in broadcasting and production management.

Te Taura Whiri i te Reo Māori

Professor Rawinia Higgins. With extensive experience in language revitalisation, governance, and policy development, with a strong academic background and leadership experience. This 18-month reappointment as Chair will provide valuable continuity of leadership at Te Taura Whiri i te Reo Māori.
Te Haumihiata Mason appointed for three years. Linguist, translator, and educator with a lifelong commitment to te reo Māori revitalisation.

Whakaata Māori

Jamie Tuuta has extensive governance experience with a strong strategic focus. This 18-month reappointment as Chair will provide strong leadership on strategic priorities.
Tiwana Tibble has been reappointed for three years. He has expertise in financial management, governance, and a background in Māori economic authorities, commercial accountancy and sector governance.
Holly Bennett has been appointed for three years. Her strong governance and business expertise will bring valuable insights.

“These entities fulfil a wide range of roles, from preserving cultural practices and archival material to engaging with communities, so their leadership reflects the depth of expertise needed to advance te reo Māori revitalisation,” Mr Potaka says.
“This kaupapa is at the heart of many homes and communities across the country so I especially want to acknowledge and thank all the outgoing members for their valuable contributions.”
Te whakapakari i te whai wāhitanga ki te reo Māori
Toi te kupu, toi te mana, toi tū te reo.
Kia atamai ngā kopounga ki ngā hinonga reo Māori whakarae e āwhina ki te whakatipu i te whai wāhitanga ki te reo Māori me ōna tikanga ki ngā kāinga me ngā hapori, e kī ana te Minita Whanaketanga Māori a Tama Potaka.
Ko ngā whakaaturanga whakaipoipo nō ngā rā o mua pēnā i te Homai te Pakipaki, ngā whakatairanga e aroha nuitia ana e te iwi, pēnā i Te Wiki o te Reo Māori, tatū atu ki te ihi, te wehi, te mana o ngā taumāhekeheke ā-motu pēnā i Te Matatini o Te Kāhui Maunga, katoa ēnei he mea tō mai i ngā mata tini, mata kanorau anō hoki ki te reo Māori me ōna tikanga. Ko ngā kōrero pūrākau mō te Māori Māori ake nei te āhua e tautoko tonu i ngā ākonga reo Māori tatū atu ki te hunga matatau i a tātou e tahuri ake ana ki tētahi ao pāpāho e matihiko haere, e matihiko haere nei.
“Ko ētahi o ngā kopounga e pānuitia ake ana e au i te rangi nei he kaiarataki i te mana ārahi, te pakihi, te pāpāho, me te whakarauoratanga reo.” E whai ake nei ko ngā hinonga me ngā kopounga:
Te Mātāwai

Ko Penetaui Kleskovic - he Pou Whakahaere Whānui o Te Aupōuri, he Kaikaunihera hoki o Ngā Tai o Tokerau Māori Ward. I tua atu i tōna tohungatanga ki te reo Māori, aua atu ngā hua e puta mai ki te poari i ana mātau ki te whakatipu rawa me te honohono ki te hapori.

Te Māngai Pāho

Kua kopounga a Erana Reedy mō te toru tau. E whai wheako ana ia i tana 40 tau i te ao pāpāho, e whakaputa ana i te ihirangi reo Māori huri noa i te reo irirangi, te pouaka whakaata, me ngā aratuku tuihono tae atu ki te tūranga o te Tumuaki o Te Reo Irirangi o Ngāti Porou me te Toihau Tuarua o Te Whakaruruhau o Ngā Reo Irirangi Māori.
Kua kopounga anō a Tamalene Painting mō te toru tau. Ko ōna pūkenga he tino matatau ki te reo Māori, ki te taha pūtea, ka mutu, he whānui ōna wheako i ngā mahi whakahaere i te pāpāho me te whakanao.

Te Taura Whiri i te Reo Māori

Te Ahorangi Rawinia Higgins. Aua atu te wā e ruku ana ia i ngā mahi o te whakarauora reo, o te mana ārahi kaupapa, oti rā, o te whakawhanake kaupapahere, he tautōhito nō te ao mātauranga, he manu taupunga tātaki tangata. E whaihua tēnei kopounga anō mō te 18 marama ki te tūranga a te Toihau ki te ukiuki o te mana whakahaere ki Te Taura Whiri i te Reo Māori.
Kua kopounga mai a Te Haumihiata Mason mō te toru tau. He tohunga wetereo, he kaiwhakamāori, he kaiwhakaako ngākau nui mō te hemo tonu atu ki te whakarauoratanga o te reo Māori.

Whakaata Māori

He tautōhito a Jamie Tuuta ki te mana ārahi kaupapa me te aronga rautaki nui. Mā tēnei kopounga anō mō te 18 marama ki te tūranga a te Toihau e whakarite he kaha te mana whakahaere mō te taha ki ngā whakaarotau rautaki.
Kua kopounga anō a Tiwana Tibble mō te toru tau. He mātanga ia i te mahi whakahaere pūtea, mana ārahi kaupapa, kua haere mai hoki ia i te ao o ngā mana ōhanga Māori, te mahi tiaki pūtea arumoni me te mana ārahi rāngai.
Kua kopounga a Holly Bennett mō te toru tau. E hia nei ngā hua e puta mai ai i tana mātau ki te mahi mana ārahi kaupapa me te pakihi.

“He whānui ngā tūranga e kawea ana e ēnei hinonga, mai i te penapena o ngā tikanga ahurea me ngā rawa pūranga tae atu ki te hononga atu ki ngā hapori, nō reira e whakaataria ana e tā rātou mana whakahaere te hōhonu o te tohungatanga e tika ana ki te kōkiri whakamua i te whakarauoratanga o te reo Māori,” e kī ana a Minita Potaka.
“I ngā tini kāinga, hapori hoki huri noa i te motu, kāore i tua atu, kāore i tua mai i tēnei kaupapa, nō reira, kāore e ārikarika te mihi me te maioha atu ki ngā kaiwhiri tahito me ā rātou takoha puiaki ki te kaupapa.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 10:06:54 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124740</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Going for Growth: More affordable building products</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/going-growth-more-affordable-building-products</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Just-passed legislation is expected to put up to 250,000 more building products on shelves this year alone - giving Kiwis building and renovating their homes more choice to fit their budgets, Building and Construction Minister Chris Penk says.
“Making it easier and more affordable to build in New Zealand is a central pillar in this Government’s Going for Growth plan to get the economy back on track.
“That’s why we have made changes to the Building Act to reduce barriers for using high-quality building products imported from overseas.
“The status quo is unacceptable. Construction costs have risen a staggering 40 percent since 2019, spurred on by a lack of competition in the building system. Bringing hundreds of thousands of new options into the market will put downward pressure on prices.
“Builders and designers have long called for this change, so they can get the best deals on goods and materials countries like Australia are already benefiting from.
“We expect that from July, more than 12,000 essential products - including plasterboard, cladding, and insulation - will be cleared for use through cited standards in the new Building Product Specifications pathway. Building Consent Authorities must accept them, so long as the products are used as intended.
“Increasing options on the market is critically important for improving supply chain resilience. Giving our tradespeople alternatives to turn to during product shortages will allow projects to continue without delays.
“Local manufacturers will also benefit from being able to test their products against internationally accepted standards, opening the door to valuable export markets.
“Work is already underway to establish robust regulations for recognising new products and standards, ensuring only top-quality materials enter the market. This includes targeted consultation with industry leaders and local government.”
Note to editors:

Under the new system:

The Minister for Building and Construction will be able to issue a notice that recognises groups of overseas product standards and standards certification schemes for use in New Zealand.
A new&nbsp;building product specifications pathway will be introduced to streamline the process of citing international product standards that can be used with acceptable solutions or verification methods to establish compliance with the building code.
Building Consent Authorities will be required to accept building products and methods that have been certified by an overseas product certification scheme and recognised by the Ministry of Business, Innovation and Employment.


The Building (Overseas Building Products, Standards, and Certification Schemes) Amendment Bill responds to recommendations from the Commerce Commission’s 2022 market study into residential building supplies, which highlighted issues with the current lack of competition for the supply and acquisition of building products.&nbsp;&nbsp;

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 09:37:50 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124739</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Reducing ambiguity about what is reasonably practicable for health and safety compliance</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/reducing-ambiguity-about-what-reasonably-practicable-health-and-safety-compliance</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Workplace Relations and Safety Minister Brooke van Velden says safe harbours of deemed compliance will be created to increase business and worker certainty about what they need to do to comply with their health and safety duties.
Approved Codes of Practice (ACOPs) are practical guidelines to help people in specific sectors and industries to comply with their health and safety duties.
“Health and safety compliance is based on people doing what is ‘reasonably practicable’ to manage risks, yet I’ve heard time and time again that many people don’t know what ‘reasonably practicable’ actually looks like. There is a demand for more and better guidance,” says Ms van Velden.
“As part of my health and safety reform, I am making a change to the ACOP model to reassure people that if they comply with an ACOP, they have done enough to meet their health and safety duties.
“In the absence of clear regulations and guidance, an entire health and safety industry has developed, which comes at a cost to businesses, consumers and taxpayers. You should not have to hire a health and safety consultant just to understand whether or not you are compliant with the law.
“Public consultation feedback indicated that uncertainty about what to do has led to overcompliance and a focus on paperwork instead of actions. I want to ensure that businesses and workers know what they need to do.”
“My health and safety reform will see a shift from a reliance on regulations to greater use of ACOPs. Regulations often remain in place that are outdated, not fit for purpose, and often overly complex. Changing regulations can often take years. Even if new regulations are made, the pace of change in industry practices and technology means that they can rapidly become out of date.
“ACOPs may be sector based but can also be used to help businesses know what ‘reasonably practicable’ means for specific issues that may occur across a range of sectors. They will likely be a useful tool for supporting innovation by responding to new and emerging industries where certainty about the risks would not yet warrant regulations.
“Rather than having WorkSafe lead this process exclusively, I am also introducing a change to allow individuals and groups, such as industry organisations, to initiate work on ACOPs to speed things up and ensure they reflect what will work in practice and what makes sense for those who deal with these risks every day.
“As the Minister of Workplace Relations and Safety I will approve each new ACOP against a set of standards to ensure they are high quality.”
These changes are part of the wider health and safety system reform and will be progressed through changes to legislation later this year.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Apr 2025 05:00:42 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124738</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Backing builders by cracking down on cowboys</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/backing-builders-cracking-down-cowboys</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government is backing builders by making changes so Kiwis will more easily be able to identify high-quality, trusted professionals to carry out work on their homes, Building and Construction Minister Chris Penk says.
“Most tradies are highly skilled and trustworthy, but the industry tells me high-profile examples of poor workmanship are tarring the good with the bad. I have also heard that Kiwis want assurances that the Government’s work to unblock the building consent system won’t lead to corners being cut.
“There is an urgent need to strip back the layers of regulation choking productivity in the building system. Builders are waiting too long for the necessary paperwork to get on with the job adds costs for homeowners. That’s why we are hammering away at an ambitious programme of reforms, including a proposal that will enable trusted tradespeople to sign-off their own work.
“This will make it easier and more affordable to deliver new homes, but it’s important that there are checks in the system to protect against shoddy work.
“New rules announced today will help increase accountability and give consumers a clear path forward if things go wrong.“Master Builders welcome these changes, which will be significant in helping to bolster the reputation of the building and construction profession, and include:

Strengthening the disciplinary process and introducing greater transparency by giving the Licensed Building Practitioners Registrar, who oversee the registration of Licensed Building Practitioners (LBP), more tools and publishing details of builders who have been suspended.
Establishing a new waterproofing licence class for LBPs so consumers can be confident those completing wet area bathrooms and level-entry showers are suitably qualified and accountable for their work.
Improving the complaints processes for licensed electrical workers, and licensed plumbers, gasfitters and drainlayers by enabling the Registrars to initiate investigations more easily and enabling the creation of Codes of Ethics to promote professional standards of behaviour.

“We want builders to take pride in their work, and homeowners to have peace of mind about the quality of workmanship carried out. New rules will give the small minority of bad operators the chance to shape up or ship out.“This is just the beginning. More reforms are on the way to crack down on cowboy builders - including increasing penalties for careless work.”Notes to editors:
The changes will apply to work completed by licensed electrical workers, licensed building practitioners and plumbers, gasfitters and drainlayers, and are expected to come into force in 2026.

More information can be found on the MBIE Building Performance website: https://www.building.govt.nz/about-building-performance/all-news-and-updates/licensing-changes-for-building-professionals

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 17:14:26 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124737</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Unacceptable payment by KiwiRail</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/unacceptable-payment-kiwirail</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Rail Minister Winston Peters has described KiwiRail’s payment of $8 million to a management consultancy firm as unacceptable.
“We are not criticising McKinsey, whose services were tendered in a lawful and competitive manner. We are criticising the decision to pay that sum,” says Mr Peters.
KiwiRail engaged McKinsey on 6 December 2023, but did not tell the Government about it until 7 February 2024 or disclose the value of the payment to Ministers until 6 June 2024. The Ombudsman determined recently that the total payment value should be released.
“We want railways to succeed for this country, and we have provided KiwiRail with a rock-solid commercial foundation to do that,” says Mr Peters.
“KiwiRail is receiving new locomotives and wagons, modern and efficient mechanical depots, better systems to manage these assets, long-term infrastructure certainty like road freight operators have with the State Highways, and we have sorted the ferry replacement – again.
“The response to a difficult balance sheet should not be to bring in management consultants. This would not have happened had they told us their plans.
“The response should be to tighten spending, lift service quality and build the customer base, and that is exactly what KiwiRail is now doing.
“Freight is about schedule reliability. If you can prove to customers that you turn up when you say you will, then loyalty will grow and volumes and earnings will follow.
“We are pleased KiwiRail is focussed on this. Reliability is strong, especially for major industry customers, and Interislander is delivering near 100% reliability. Safety is heading in the right direction too.
“Earnings are on target and the company has achieved $30 million in savings so far this year. KiwiRail has firm targets to attract more volume from existing and new customers, and we were pleased to see a real customer strategy laid bare in recent discussions with KiwiRail’s senior management,” says Mr Peters.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 13:04:38 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124736</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Investing in injury prevention in the manufacturing sector</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/investing-injury-prevention-manufacturing-sector</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ACC’s investment in New Zealand’s crucial manufacturing sector is a significant step to help reduce injuries, keep workers safe, and support economic growth, say ACC Minister Scott Simpson and Small Business and Manufacturing Minister Chris Penk.
“My top priority with ACC is to address its declining performance and ensure the scheme remains financially sustainable for current and future generations. One of the best ways to both enhance the health and wellbeing of Kiwis and keep costs down is to prevent injuries from happening in the first place,” says Mr Simpson.
“That’s why I welcome the steps ACC is taking to drive better health outcomes for workers and businesses in manufacturing.”
In 2024, ACC worked with the Employers and Manufacturers Association to co-design a Harm Reduction Action Plan for Manufacturing, which proposed a series of solutions. ACC is now seeking a supplier who can combine their own insights with those from the industry, to develop and implement evidence-based initiatives that will reduce the incidence and severity of injuries and their associated costs.
“Manufacturing is a powerful driver for economic growth in New Zealand, contributing more than 60 per cent of our exports and employing nearly 230,000 people across 23,000 business,” Mr Penk says.&nbsp;
“However, it stands out as the only major industry where work-related injury rates have not declined over the past decade. As a high-risk sector, manufacturing is prioritised by ACC to address the growing cost of claims in the working-age population.
“Now is the time to implement some long-term initiatives to reduce the high rate of injuries in manufacturing. By reducing workplace harm, we can lower costs for businesses and ensure our manufacturers continue driving economic growth."
“The total annual ACC claims costs for the manufacturing sector are more than $165 million and growing. I am pleased that ACC is committed to working with the industry to make a difference, preventing harm and helping address rapidly rising costs,” says Mr Simpson.
“I expect ACC to conduct a robust procurement process and I look forward to seeing the visions for the sector turn into reality.”
Responses to the tender must be submitted via the&nbsp;New Zealand Government Electronic Tender Service (GETS) or&nbsp;procurement@acc.co.nz by 12pm, Tuesday 13 May 2025.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 10:35:15 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124735</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Health and safety governance and management change coming </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/health-and-safety-governance-and-management-change-coming</link>
  <description><![CDATA[The Government has agreed to clarify the distinction between governance and operational management health and safety responsibilities to reduce directors’ fear and risks of overcompliance, Workplace Relations and Safety Minister Brooke van Velden announced today.
The Government is delivering on an ACT-National Coalition Agreement to reform New Zealand’s health and safety laws and regulations.
“Throughout the public consultation and the roadshow on the health and safety law, I heard from business owners and company directors that they are unclear about their health and safety duties under the Health and Safety at Work Act in both large and small businesses.
“Feedback shared by many is that there is overcompliance as many directors think they need to do more than they should, and directors and management are also duplicating work,” says Ms van Velden.
“Today, I am announcing a change in the legislation to specify that the day-to-day management of health and safety risks is to be left to managers so that directors and boards can focus on governance and the strategic oversight of the business.”
This change is part of the wider health and safety system reform and will be progressed through changes to legislation later this year.
“Making this distinction will enhance the effectiveness of health and safety governance and the outcomes we can achieve in the health and safety system.
“Work is continuing to ensure this is effective and fit-for-purpose and I intend to return to Cabinet to seek agreement on the specific details of this change,” says Ms van Velden.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 05:00:14 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124734</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Plain Language Act Repeal Bill passes first reading</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/plain-language-act-repeal-bill-passes-first-reading</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Legislation to repeal the Plain Language Act, which is a waste of time and money, has passed its first reading in Parliament today, Public Service Minister Judith Collins says.
“The Act, implemented by the previous government, compelled public service agencies to appoint designated 'plain language officers' and implement specific activities,” Ms Collins says.
“Rather than fix a problem, it created a problem whereby plain language officers had to be appointed, the Public Service Commission had to produce guidance documents and then agencies had to report to someone on something no one was quite clear on.
“That takes time, and time is money. It’s this sort of wasteful spending on bureaucracy that the Government is calling time on.
Repealing the Act means agencies will no longer be required to have a designated plain language officer.&nbsp;
“We need to trust the judgment and expertise of our public servants to communicate in language every taxpayer can grasp – without the need for designated officers or legal compulsion,” Ms Collins says.
“Repealing this Act cuts red tape and will allow the public service to get on with what really matters, which is delivering services for New Zealanders.”
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:42:54 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124732</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Government seeks to simplify Fringe Benefit Tax rules</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/government-seeks-simplify-fringe-benefit-tax-rules</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Inland Revenue is launching public consultation on proposals to make the Fringe Benefit Tax (FBT) rules easier&nbsp;and to reduce compliance costs for taxpayers, Revenue Minister Simon Watts says.
FBT is a tax payable when the following benefits are supplied to employees or shareholder-employees:

low interest/interest-free loans
free, subsidised, or discounted goods and services
employer contributions to sick, accident or death funds, superannuation schemes and specified insurance policies
motor vehicles available for private use
unclassified fringe benefits.

“Public feedback will help shape final proposals which Government will consider this year. The proposals have also been designed to be broadly fiscally neutral as the changes will focus on enhancing the integrity of the tax system,” Mr Watts says.
“Inland Revenue has been working with private sector experts to develop practical options for modernising the rules and to reduce compliance costs. We have already heard a lot of feedback from small businesses, and therefore, Inland Revenue has incorporated a proposal to move away from a focus on absolute accuracy of usage and instead adopting a ‘close enough is good enough’ approach which could take a lot of the compliance cost sting out of FBT.
“The focus of the proposals in the consultation document relates to motor vehicles and other small benefits and aims to simplify requirements and ease the compliance cost burden.
“The&nbsp;Fringe Benefit Tax was launched 40 years ago and, in that time, only a limited number of minor adjustments have been made to the rules.
“It is a quite fitting coincidence that consultation is being launched on the 40th anniversary of fringe benefit tax coming into effect.”
The consultation document is available at https://www.taxpolicy.ird.govt.nz/consultation/2025/fbt-options-for-change with consultation closing on 5 May.
]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 17:00:39 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124731</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Supporting better rehabilitation rates for injured Kiwis</title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/supporting-better-rehabilitation-rates-injured-kiwis</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Updates to ACC’s Accredited Employers Programme taking effect today are designed to improve workplace injury rehabilitation for around one-fifth of New Zealand’s workforce and support our economic growth, says ACC Minister Scott Simpson.
“ACC’s fundamental purpose is to prevent injuries and get injured Kiwis back to independence as soon as possible. But rehabilitation rates have been slipping over the past decade, which is why they’re a crucial focus for me as I look to significantly improve ACC’s performance and long-term financial sustainability,” says Mr Simpson.
“The Accredited Employers Programme plays a big role in that – more than one in five full-time equivalent employees in New Zealand work for an accredited employer. I welcome the improvements ACC has made to enhance health and recovery outcomes for this substantial part of our workforce.”
The Programme allows sufficiently large employers to manage their employees’ claims for work injuries and occupational diseases in-house. In return for taking on the financial liability and claim management of work injuries, accredited employers receive a reduction in their work account levy.
The changes taking effect today include updates to improve performance monitoring and the way employers handle claims. These are the first substantive updates to the programme since its inception in 2000.
“The Accredited Employers Programme provides employers with a financial incentive to reduce workplace injuries and support staff to return to independence quickly,” says Mr Simpson.
“Ensuring employers help their employees get back to health and return to work makes absolute sense, as rehabilitation rates need serious improvement. These changes will ensure employers are meeting their obligations and providing the right support to their employees.”
Notes to editors
About the Accredited Employers Programme:

The Accredited Employers Programme includes some of New Zealand’s largest employers. There are around 130 employers in the programme, encompassing approximately 435,000 full time equivalent (FTE) employees, around 23 per cent of New Zealand’s total FTEs.
To remain in the Programme, Accredited Employers undertake an annual accreditation process, including an assessment, to ensure they are meeting all the requirements for the programme.

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:57:51 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124729</guid>
    </item>
<item>
  <title>Northland water security receives $41m boost </title>
  <link>https://www.beehive.govt.nz/release/northland-water-security-receives-41m-boost</link>
  <description><![CDATA[Water projects in Northland will receive up to $41.5 million from the Regional Infrastructure Fund to significantly increase the region’s water security and unlock economic growth, Regional Development Minister Shane Jones says.
“These water projects together will significantly improve water storage and security in the Mid Far North and enable economic growth through consistent access to water and irrigation infrastructure for horticulture and land development,” Mr Jones says.
The funded projects are:

Otawere Pipeline&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; $24m loan
Kaipara Pipeline&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp; $17.5m loan

The Otawere Pipeline project will see Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust consolidate the Otawere Reservoir on Waitangi River and expand its distribution network by 15km.
“This will provide water to a larger area of the community, and link to other key Mid Far North water storage projects to increase land-change opportunities in Kaikohe and surrounding areas,” Mr Jones says.
When it is completed, the infrastructure will enable 1600ha of productive land for Matawii, Waimate North and Mid North. The project will also employ 52 full-time staff during construction.
Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust will also receive up to $17.5m in the form of a loan to construct a 22km pipeline connecting the trust’s recently completed reservoir near Te Kopuru, to Dargaville.
“The Kaipara pipeline will extend to around 3000ha of prospective horticulture land between Te Kopuru and Dargaville and to Silver Fern Farm’s processing plant, the largest employer in the area.
“The plant faces challenges maintaining the continuous water supply it needs to keep operating throughout summer. Extending the pipeline to the processing plant will ensure a reliable water supply and continuous peak season operation,” Mr Jones says.
As part of this project, Te Tai Tokerau Water Trust and Kaipara District Council will combine the delivery of the Kaipara pipeline with an existing $7.8m Regional Infrastructure Fund flood resilience project, the Dargaville to Te Kōpuru stopbank upgrade.
The combined approach will lead to potential savings of $3m and a shorter delivery time through efficiencies across both projects.
“The Government’s investment in water is addressing barriers to development in regions like Northland, where a consistent water source is needed to unlock economic, environmental, and recreational resources for its communities,” Mr Jones says.
Editor’s note

The Regional Infrastructure Fund is a capital fund with the primary purpose of accelerating infrastructure projects, particularly with a focus on water storage, energy, and resilience, that will make a difference in the regions.
Funding is approved in principle and announced, after which contracts are negotiated. Some funding may depend on updated information as agreed in contract negotiation. Payments are made once agreed milestones are met. These are set as part of contract negotiations and differ from project to project.
The Dargaville to Te Kōpuru Stopbank Upgrades project funding was approved by the Regional Development Ministers Group in July 2024.

]]></description>
  <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 14:52:53 +1300</pubDate>
    <dc:creator>beehive.govt.nz</dc:creator>
    <guid isPermaLink="true">https://www.beehive.govt.nz/124728</guid>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
